<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Odes of Horace the best of lyrick poets contayning much morallity, and sweetnesse. Selected, and translated by Sr: T:H: 1625.</title>
            <title>Selections. English</title>
            <author>Horace.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1625</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 93 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 39 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A03674</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 13800</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S104228</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99839967</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99839967</idno>
            <idno type="VID">4433</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A03674)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 4433)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1243:7)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Odes of Horace the best of lyrick poets contayning much morallity, and sweetnesse. Selected, and translated by Sr: T:H: 1625.</title>
                  <title>Selections. English</title>
                  <author>Horace.</author>
                  <author>T.H., Sir (Thomas Hawkins), d. 1640.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[10], 67, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By A[ugustine]: M[athewes]: for Will: Lee and are to be sold at his shoppe in Fleet-street, at the signe of the Goulden Bucke,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Imprinted at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>[1625]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Sr: T:H: = Sir Thomas Hawkins.</note>
                  <note>Includes four of the Epodes.</note>
                  <note>The title page is engraved.</note>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-09</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:4433:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:4433:1"/>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <p>ODES OF HORACE The beſt of Lyrick Poets, <hi>Contayning much morallity, and ſweetneſse.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Selected, and Tranſlated by S<hi rend="sup">r</hi>: T: H:</hi> 1625</p>
                  <p>Imprinted at London by A: M: for Will: Lée and are to be ſold at his ſhoppe in Fleet: ſtreet: at the ſigne of the Goolden Bucke</p>
               </figure>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:4433:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:4433:2"/>
            <head>To the Reader.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Riendly, and generous <hi>Reader)</hi> I preſent not <hi>Horace</hi> to thee, in his natiue luſtre, nor Language. Take theſe rather (if ſo thou pleaſe) for a reflection, from that brighter body of his li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing <hi>Odes.</hi> Behold in them <hi>Moralitie</hi> touched, and <hi>Vertue</hi> heightned, with cleareneſſe of <hi>Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit,</hi> and accurateneſſe of <hi>Iudgement.</hi> Theſe haue I ſelected amongſt many, not with deſire to preſcribe the ſame choiſe to others, as a rule; nor yet with any diffidence in my own election. <hi>Abundat quiſ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> ſuo ſenſu.</hi> When in a Garden we gather a <hi>Coronet</hi> of Flowres, wee intend not the totall beautie of that faire piece of proſpectiue, but particular ornament, and entermingled delight. Theſe ſupply both. But many (no doubt) will ſay, <hi>Horace</hi> is by mee forſaken, his <hi>Lyrick</hi> ſoftneſſe, and emphaticall
<pb facs="tcp:4433:3"/> 
               <hi>Muſe</hi> maymed: That in all there is a generall defection from his genuine Harmony. Thoſe I muſt tell, I haue in this Tranſlation, rather ſought his <hi>Spirit,</hi> then <hi>Numbers;</hi> yet the <hi>Mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſique</hi> of Verſe not neglected neither, ſince the Engliſh eare better heareth the <hi>Diſtick,</hi> and findeth that ſweetneſſe, and ayre in theſe pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portions, which the <hi>Latine</hi> affecteth, and (que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtionleſſe) attaineth in <hi>Saphick</hi> or <hi>Iambick</hi> mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures. Some will vrge againe, why were not theſe Wreathes of morall, and ſerious <hi>Odes,</hi> for the more varietie, and generall entertaine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of moſt, mixed with his wanton and looſer ſtraines of <hi>Poeſie?</hi> Theſe I anſwer, and with it conclude. The <hi>Tranſlatour</hi> of theſe, had rather teach Vertue to the modeſt, then diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer Vice to the diſſolute. The ſtreames of <hi>Helicon,</hi> are cleare, and Chryſtalline. Drinke thou goodneſſe from theſe purer Fountaines, whileſt ſuch take vnhappy draughts, from the troubled and muddy waters of <hi>Senſuality.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb facs="tcp:4433:3"/>
            <head>Jn Fideliſsimum <hi>HORATII</hi> inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pretem T. H. <hi>Equitem Auratum.</hi>
            </head>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>ANglia</hi> nunc Muſis dominatur; <hi>Horatius An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glus</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Laetatur; Lyrico victa<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> 
                  <hi>Roma</hi> ſuo est;</l>
               <l>Talia, linguarum Dominam mirabere poſſe</l>
               <l>Dicere; non magis eſt, haec potuiſſe, rudem?</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Flaccus</hi> mutatur, remanet ſed candor in Illo;</l>
               <l>Plumeus, in doctas, concidit imber, aquas;</l>
               <l>Sic tibi gent is honos, noſtrae tibi debita linguae</l>
               <l>Gloria; &amp; <hi>Angliacae</hi> Laurea vitta Comae.</l>
            </lg>
            <closer>
               <signed>F. L.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb facs="tcp:4433:4"/>
            <head>To the Tranſlatour.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>VVHat ſhal I fi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſt commend? your happy choice</l>
               <l>Of this moſt vſefull <hi>Poet?</hi> or your skill,</l>
               <l>To make the <hi>Eccho</hi> equall with the voice,</l>
               <l>And trace the Lines drawne by the <hi>Authors</hi> quill?</l>
               <l>The <hi>Latine</hi> Writers by vnlearned hands,</l>
               <l>In forraine Robes vnwillingly are dreſt,</l>
               <l>But thus inuited into other Lands,</l>
               <l>Are glad to change their tongue at ſuch requeſt.</l>
               <l>The good, which in our minds their labours breed,</l>
               <l>Layes open to their Fame a larger way.</l>
               <l>Theſe ſtrangers <hi>England</hi> with rich plentie feed,</l>
               <l>Which with our Countreys freedome we repay:</l>
               <l>When ſitting in pure Language like a Throne,</l>
               <l>They proue as great with vs, as with their owne.</l>
            </lg>
            <closer>
               <signed>Iohn Beaumont.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb facs="tcp:4433:4"/>
            <head>To his worthie Friend, S<hi rend="sup">r.</hi> 
               <hi>T. H.</hi> Knight, vpon his Tranſlation.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>VVHile to thy Time the Lyrick Poet ſings,</l>
               <l>And takes new graces fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thy tuned ſtrings;</l>
               <l>Behold, whole Quires of Muſes, reddy ſtand,</l>
               <l>To beg like fauour at thy curious hand.</l>
               <l>Who would not ioyne with them, and moue the ſame,</l>
               <l>That ſees this One ſo happie in thy Name?</l>
               <l>We whom the <hi>Romans</hi> held for dull and weake,</l>
               <l>Now teach their best of Poets how to ſpeake.</l>
               <l>They need not lay to thee, the want of skill,</l>
               <l>Of Muſick, or of Muſes, hee that will,</l>
               <l>May heare them both expreſt by thee, in vaines</l>
               <l>Equall, if not beyond the <hi>Roman</hi> ſtraines.</l>
            </lg>
            <closer>
               <signed>George Forteſcue.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb facs="tcp:4433:5"/>
            <head>To my Noble Friend, Sir <hi>T. H.</hi> Knight.</head>
            <lg>
               <head>An O de in pure l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>bick feet.</head>
               <l>I Knew before thy dainty tuch,</l>
               <l>Vpon the Lordly Violl:</l>
               <l>But of thy Lyre who knew ſo much</l>
               <l>Before this happy triall?</l>
               <l>So tuned is thy ſacred Harpe,</l>
               <l>To make her <hi>eccho</hi> ſweetly ſharpe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>I wote not how to praiſe inough</l>
               <l>Thy Muſick and thy Muſes:</l>
               <l>Thy Gloſſe ſo ſmooth, the Text ſo tough,</l>
               <l>Be Iudge, who both peruſes.</l>
               <l>Thy choice of Odes is alſo chaſte,</l>
               <l>No want it hath, it hath no waſte.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>A grace it is for any Knight,</l>
               <l>A ſtately Steed to ſtable:</l>
               <l>But vnto <hi>Pegaſus</hi> the light</l>
               <l>Is any comparable?</l>
               <l>No Courſer of ſo comly Courſe,</l>
               <l>Was euer as the winged <hi>Horſe.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>That <hi>Aſtrophill,</hi> of Arts the life, <note place="margin">S. <hi>Phi. Sidney.</hi>
                  </note>
               </l>
               <l>A <hi>Knight</hi> was, and a <hi>Poet:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>So was the Man, who tooke to wife <note place="margin">S. <hi>Geof. Chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cer.</hi>
                  </note>
               </l>
               <l>The Daughter of <hi>La-Roët.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>So Thou that haſt reſeru'd a parte,</l>
               <l>To rouze my <hi>Iohnſon,</hi> and his <hi>Arte.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Receiue the while my lowly Verſe</l>
               <l>to waite vpon thy Muſes:</l>
               <l>Who ca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>not halfe thy worth reherſe,</l>
               <l>My braine that height refuſes.</l>
               <l>Beueath thy <hi>Meede</hi> is all my praiſe;</l>
               <l>That, asks a Crowne of holy <hi>Baies.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <closer>
               <signed>Hugh Holland.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb facs="tcp:4433:5"/>
            <head>In laudem Authoris. <hi>Oda,</hi> In quâ Verſiones nonnullae ab eodem factae praenotantur.</head>
            <l>QValis Sonoro voluitur alueo</l>
            <l>Veruis <hi>Hydaſpes</hi> imbribus intumens,</l>
            <l>Ripaeque debellator vndas</l>
            <l>Per teneras rapit amnis herbas.</l>
            <l>
               <hi>Horatiano</hi> talis ab aequore</l>
            <l>Linguae decorus flumine patriae</l>
            <l>Manas, &amp; inſpiras amorem</l>
            <l>Cordibus, imperio Camoe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ae.</l>
            <l>Scu cantu auit is Regibus editum <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Moecenas</hi> Ataui<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> &amp;c. Iam ſatis terris, &amp;c.</note>
            </l>
            <l>H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>roa promis: ſeu violentiùs</l>
            <l>Vndas retorquentem minacis</l>
            <l>
               <hi>Tibridos</hi> in dominam Orbis vrbem</l>
            <l>Cantas <hi>Etruſci</hi> littoris aggerem:</l>
            <l>Vitae ipſe purus ſeu canis integ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>um; <note place="margin">Integer vit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, &amp;c. Quis deſiderio, &amp;c. <hi>Dianam</hi> tene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rae, &amp;c. O Diua gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum, &amp;c.</note>
            </l>
            <l>Raptumque non deduci ab Orco</l>
            <l>
               <hi>Quinctilium</hi> lacrymis perurges.</l>
            <l>Per te <hi>Dianam</hi> dicere Virgines</l>
            <l>Nouere. <hi>Diuam,</hi> quae regit <hi>Antium,</hi>
            </l>
            <l>Eheu! quid vrges in <hi>Britannos</hi>
            </l>
            <l>
               <hi>Caeſareis</hi> comitem ire turmis?</l>
            <l>Nunc quaeris auro quis color abdito. <note place="margin">Nullus argen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to, &amp;c. Aequam me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mento, &amp;c. Non ſemper imbres, &amp;c. Beatus ilbe, qul, &amp;c. Exegi monu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentum, &amp;c.</note>
            </l>
            <l>Nunc mentis ornas aequanimae fidem.</l>
            <l>Nunc <hi>Myſtis</hi> extincti calores</l>
            <l>
               <hi>Picrijs</hi> moderaris vndis.</l>
            <l>Tandem beato ruris in otio</l>
            <l>Laudas agentes. His tibi ſacula</l>
            <l>Poſt mille duraturum, &amp; vltra</l>
            <l>Carminibus monum<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ntum adornas.</l>
            <closer>
               <signed>G. D.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb facs="tcp:4433:6"/>
            <head>
               <hi>V. Cl. T. H.</hi> Equiti Aurato, Suo.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>ANglica Romani</hi> iam prodit Muſa leporis</l>
               <l>Aemula, nec caeptis excidit illa ſuis.</l>
               <l>Quàm ſibi <hi>Narciſſo</hi> ſimilis <hi>Narciſſus</hi> in vndis,</l>
               <l>Tam ſimilis noſtras <hi>Flacce Poeta</hi> tibi.</l>
               <l>Quàm ſimilis linguae rediuiuis vocibus <hi>Echo</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Permeat aethereas, Nympha canora, plagas,</l>
               <l>Tam ſimilis Lyricae respondet noſtra Camoenae,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Romanum<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan>
                  </hi> melos <hi>Anglica</hi> plectra mouent.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Romanas</hi> tenuit <hi>Romanus Horatius</hi> aures,</l>
               <l>Nunc <hi>Anglas Anglus</hi> non tenet ille minùs.</l>
               <l>Nam quod dulce ſonat <hi>Romanis Appula</hi> Muſa.</l>
               <l>Hoc reſonas <hi>Anglis Cantia</hi> Muſa tuis.</l>
            </lg>
            <closer>
               <signed>I. CHAPPERLINVS.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="odes">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:4433:6"/>
            <head>ODES OF HORACE.</head>
            <div n="1" type="book">
               <head>The Firſt Booke.</head>
               <div n="1" type="ode">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Ode.</hi> I. To MAECENAS.</head>
                  <argument>
                     <p>All things pleaſe not all men. <hi>HORACE</hi> moſt eſpecially affecteth the name of a <hi>Lyrick</hi> Poet.</p>
                  </argument>
                  <lg>
                     <head>Maecenas atavis.</head>
                     <l>
                        <hi>MAecenas</hi> ſprung from Grandſire Kings deſcent,</l>
                     <l>O, my defence, and ſweeteſt ornament.</l>
                     <l>There are, who in their Chariots ſpeedy flight,</l>
                     <l>To rayſe <hi>Olimpique</hi> duſt, doe take delight:</l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:4433:7"/>
                     <l>And hauing with chaſſ'd wheeles, the goale declin'd,</l>
                     <l>For Conqueſt's meed, haue ſtile of gods aſsign'd.</l>
                     <l>This man, if wauering Citizens contend,</l>
                     <l>His worth, with threefold hohours to commend:</l>
                     <l>That other, if he in his Garnier ſtores,</l>
                     <l>What euer hath beene ſwept from <hi>Lybian</hi> flores,</l>
                     <l>From painefull Tillage, and the Countreys loue,</l>
                     <l>The wealth of <hi>Attalus</hi> can neuer moue,</l>
                     <l>That he a Marriner in feare of loſſe,</l>
                     <l>With <hi>Cyprian</hi> Barke <hi>Myrto<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>an</hi> Seas ſhould croſſe.</l>
                     <l>When Southweſt windes, <hi>Icarian</hi> waues doe raiſe,</l>
                     <l>The Mercha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t reſt, &amp; Countrey graunge doth praiſe;</l>
                     <l>Straight his torne Veſſell, he repayres againe,</l>
                     <l>The force of want vnable to ſuſtaine.</l>
                     <l>Some others vſe, old <hi>Maſsique</hi> Wines to ply,</l>
                     <l>Nor from the day, ſome part to take deny;</l>
                     <l>Now, ſeeking vnder <hi>Arbutt's</hi> ſhade to cling,</l>
                     <l>Now neere the ſoft head of ſome gentle Spring.</l>
                     <l>In Tents, and Trumpets Eccho ſome delight,</l>
                     <l>Mixt with the Flute, and Warres that Mothers fright</l>
                     <l>In Fields the Hunter on the coldeſt day,</l>
                     <l>Forgetfull of his tender Wife, doth ſtay:</l>
                     <l>Whither his faithfull doggs, haue view'd the Hinde,</l>
                     <l>Or, <hi>Marſyan</hi> Bore his round netts haue vntwin'd.</l>
                     <l>Me, <hi>Iuy</hi> the reward, for Learned browes.</l>
                     <l>A place, among ſupernall gods allowes</l>
                     <l>Light qui<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>es of Wood Nymphes, that with Satyres bide,</l>
                     <l>And ſhady groues from Vulgar me diuide:</l>
                     <l>So that my Pipe <hi>Eu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>erpe</hi> not reſtraine,</l>
                     <l>Nor <hi>Polyhimne</hi> to tune my Lute refraine.</l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:4433:7"/>
                     <l>But if you me, 'mongſt <hi>Lyricks</hi> will account,</l>
                     <l>My rayſed Creaſt aboue the Starres ſhall mount.</l>
                  </lg>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="ode">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Ode</hi> II. To AVGVSTVS CAESAR.</head>
                  <argument>
                     <p>Many ſtormes are powred vpon the People of <hi>Rome</hi> in reuenge of <hi>Iulius Caeſar</hi> ſlaine. The onely hope of the Empire is placed in the ſafetie of <hi>Auguſtus.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </argument>
                  <lg>
                     <head>Iam ſatis terris.</head>
                     <l>Ioue, now on Earth, ſufficient,</l>
                     <l>Of Snow, and direfull Hayle hath ſent;</l>
                     <l>Who ſhaking Towers, with fiery hand,</l>
                     <l>Affrighted made the Citie ſtand:</l>
                     <l>He Nations ſcarr'd, left <hi>Pirrah's</hi> Raigne</l>
                     <l>New Monſters ſhould produce againe;</l>
                     <l>As earſt when <hi>Pro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>eus</hi> draue his Flock,</l>
                     <l>To feed on Cliffe of ſteepy Rock,</l>
                     <l>Then to the Elme's Tope Fiſhes claue,</l>
                     <l>Which Turtles vs'd for ſeat to haue</l>
                     <l>And Does, whom ſodaine frights diſeaſe,</l>
                     <l>Swam boldly ouer ſwelling Seas.</l>
                     <pb n="4" facs="tcp:4433:8"/>
                     <l>Our eyes haue yealow <hi>Tybers</hi> Flood</l>
                     <l>Beheld, by <hi>Tyrrhen</hi> Shores withſtood</l>
                     <l>With violence; run downe to beate,</l>
                     <l>The Tombes of Kings, and <hi>Vesta's</hi> ſeat.</l>
                     <l>While <hi>Ilia</hi> much to him complaines,</l>
                     <l>He vowes reuenge: Though <hi>Ioue</hi> diſdaines,</l>
                     <l>His wandring, and vxorious waue,</l>
                     <l>Vpon the Citie bancke, ſhould raue.</l>
                     <l>Succeeding Youth, through Parents crimes,</l>
                     <l>Impayr'd, ſhall heare that paſſed times,</l>
                     <l>Haue ſharp'ned ſwords; ſhall heare of bralls,</l>
                     <l>Wherewith the <hi>Perſian</hi> better falls.</l>
                     <l>To which god, ſhall we Vowes aſſigne,</l>
                     <l>Now, that our State affaires decline?</l>
                     <l>What prayer ſhall holy Virgin Saints,</l>
                     <l>To <hi>Vèſta</hi> yeeld, made deaſe to plaints?</l>
                     <l>To whom ſhall <hi>Ioue,</hi> the power diſpenſe,</l>
                     <l>Of expiating Sinnes offence?</l>
                     <l>(Diuining <hi>Phebus)</hi> come we pray,</l>
                     <l>Whoſe ſhoulders white the Clouds array.</l>
                     <l>Or, if thou pleaſe (ſmoth <hi>Venus)</hi> hy</l>
                     <l>About whom <hi>Sport</hi> and <hi>Pleaſures</hi> flye.</l>
                     <l>Or founder <hi>Mars,</hi> if Stocke, or Kinne,</l>
                     <l>Thou Loue, which haue neglected bene.</l>
                     <l>O, thou that cloyed art with fight,</l>
                     <l>Whom clamour, and ſmoth Helmes delight:</l>
                     <l>And <hi>Mauritanian's</hi> viſage bold,</l>
                     <l>When his ſterne Fo, he doth behold.</l>
                     <l>Or, mayſt thou (gentle <hi>Maia's</hi> Sonne)</l>
                     <l>With winged ſpeed be hither wonne.</l>
                     <pb n="5" facs="tcp:4433:8"/>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Auguſtus</hi> figure, chaung'd in thee,</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Caeſar's</hi> reuengefull friend to be.</l>
                     <l>Oh, mayſt thou (late) to heauen retyre;</l>
                     <l>Be preſent long, to <hi>Rome's</hi> deſire:</l>
                     <l>Nor may the ſpeedy blaſt of <hi>Time,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Take thee offended with our Crime.</l>
                     <l>Heere Triumphs ſeeke, and laſting fame,</l>
                     <l>Inſtil'd with <hi>Prince,</hi> and <hi>Fathers</hi> name;</l>
                     <l>Nor ſuffer <hi>Caeſar</hi> (thou our Guide)</l>
                     <l>The <hi>Medians</hi> vnreueng'd to ride.</l>
                  </lg>
               </div>
               <div n="22" type="ode">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Ode</hi> XXII. To ARISTIVS.</head>
                  <argument>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Integrity of life is euery where ſafe, which he proueth, by his owne example.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </argument>
                  <lg>
                     <head>Integer Vitae.</head>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Fvſcus)</hi> the man whoſe life's entire,</l>
                     <l>And free from ſinne, needs not deſire;</l>
                     <l>The Bow, nor Dart from <hi>Moore</hi> to borow,</l>
                     <l>Nor from full Quiuer poys'ned Arow:</l>
                     <l>Whither o're <hi>Libya's</hi> partched Sands,</l>
                     <l>Or <hi>Caucaſus,</hi> that houſeleſſe ſtands,</l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:4433:9"/>
                     <l>He takes his iourney; or thoſe places,</l>
                     <l>By which the fam'd <hi>Hydaſpes</hi> traces.</l>
                     <l>For I, while, in the <hi>Sabine</hi> Groue,</l>
                     <l>My <hi>Lalage</hi> doe chaunting roue,</l>
                     <l>From me not marking limits dew,</l>
                     <l>A Wolfe (though I vnarmed) ſlew.</l>
                     <l>A Monſter ſuch, as all exceeds,</l>
                     <l>Which in large woods fierce <hi>Daunia</hi> feeds:</l>
                     <l>Or thoſe, which <hi>Iuba's</hi> Kingdome hath,</l>
                     <l>The Deſert nourſe of Lyons wroth.</l>
                     <l>Place me in coldeſt Champaines, where,</l>
                     <l>No Sommer warmth, the Trees doth cheere:</l>
                     <l>Let me in that dull Climat reſt,</l>
                     <l>Which Cloudes, and ſullen <hi>Ioue</hi> infeſt:</l>
                     <l>Yea place me vnderneath the Carre</l>
                     <l>Of too-neere <hi>Phebus:</hi> ſeated farre</l>
                     <l>From dwellings. <hi>Lalage,</hi> I'le loue,</l>
                     <l>Whoſe ſmiles, whoſe words ſo ſweetly moue.</l>
                  </lg>
               </div>
               <div n="24" type="ode">
                  <pb facs="tcp:4433:9"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>Ode</hi> XXIV. To VIRGILL.</head>
                  <argument>
                     <p>Who immoderatly bemoned the death of <hi>Quintilius.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </argument>
                  <lg>
                     <head>Quis deſiderio ſit.</head>
                     <l>
                        <hi>MElpomene)</hi> on whom great <hi>Iupiter</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Did ſhrilleſt voice to tunefull Harpe conferre:</l>
                     <l>Declare in mournefull Notes; what ſhame, or let</l>
                     <l>Should on the loue of ſuch a friend beſet.</l>
                     <l>Shall then <hi>Quintilius</hi> ſleepe eternally?</l>
                     <l>An equall vnto whom, pure <hi>Modeſtie</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>And <hi>Iuſtice</hi> Siſter, <hi>Faith</hi> ſincere and plaine,</l>
                     <l>And naked <hi>Veritie,</hi> ſhall neuer gaine?</l>
                     <l>Of many worthy men bemoan'd he fell:</l>
                     <l>But <hi>(Virgill)</hi> no man's griefe can thine excell.</l>
                     <l>Thou (louing) doſt (alas) the gods in vaine</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Quintil us,</hi> not ſo lent thee, aske againe.</l>
                     <l>What if more ſweet, then <hi>Thracian Orphens</hi> wyre,</l>
                     <l>You Trees perſwade, to hearken to your Lyre;</l>
                     <l>Yet can you not, returne of Life command,</l>
                     <l>To ſhaddow vaine; which once with dreadfull wand,</l>
                     <pb n="8" facs="tcp:4433:10"/>
                     <l>God <hi>Mercury,</hi> vnwilling Fate t'vnlocke,</l>
                     <l>Hath forc'd to dwell among the Stygian flocke.</l>
                     <l>Tis hard I grant. "But Patience makes that light,</l>
                     <l>Which to correct, or chaunge, exceeds our might.</l>
                  </lg>
               </div>
               <div n="28" type="ode">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Ode</hi> XXVIII.</head>
                  <argument>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Architas,</hi> a Philoſopher and Geometrician is preſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, anſwering to a certaine Marriner, that all men muſt dye, and entreating him, that hee would not ſuffer his body to lie on the ſhore vnburied.</p>
                  </argument>
                  <lg>
                     <head>Te Maris, &amp; Terrae.</head>
                     <l>THee, who the Sea, Earth, Sands, that none can tell</l>
                     <l>To bound with meaſure, knew'ſt <hi>(Architas)</hi> well.</l>
                     <l>The poore gift of a little duſt confiries,</l>
                     <l>And neere vnto the Matine ſhore enſhrines:</l>
                     <l>Nor could it any helpe, or profit bee,</l>
                     <l>Death being ready ſtill to call for thee;</l>
                     <l>Thoſe ay'rie manſions to enquire from hence,</l>
                     <l>And ſearch in mind the Heau'ns circumference.</l>
                     <l>The Syre of <hi>Pelops,</hi> who with Gods did feaſt,</l>
                     <l>And aged <hi>Tython,</hi> ſhrunke at Deaths arreſt:</l>
                     <l>And <hi>Minos,</hi> to <hi>Ioues</hi> Councells call'd, was ſlaine,</l>
                     <l>And <hi>Panthois</hi> dyed, let out of Hell againe,</l>
                     <pb n="9" facs="tcp:4433:10"/>
                     <l>Though he with Shield affixed, prouing well</l>
                     <l>That his firſt Birth in <hi>Troian</hi> ages fell,</l>
                     <l>Affirm'd, that death nought kill'd, but nerues, &amp; skin:</l>
                     <l>(No man in Natures power was better ſeene:)</l>
                     <l>But wee into one ſelfe ſame night doe fall,</l>
                     <l>And muſt the paths of Death tread once for all.</l>
                     <l>The Furies, ſome to games of <hi>Mars</hi> apply</l>
                     <l>The greedy Sayler, drencht in Seas doth lie.</l>
                     <l>In death both young and old by heapes do ioyne;</l>
                     <l>Nor any head eſcapes ſad <hi>Proſerpine.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Yea, the South-wind, crooked <hi>Orions</hi> mate,</l>
                     <l>Or'e whelm'd me in <hi>Illyrian</hi> waues of late:</l>
                     <l>But bee thou pleaſed (gentle Marriner,)</l>
                     <l>MY bones, and head, in looſe ſand to interre.</l>
                     <l>Which done (ſo thou be ſafe) may th' Eaſterne wind,</l>
                     <l>That moues <hi>Heſperian</hi> billowes be aſſign'd,</l>
                     <l>To bluſter lowdly in <hi>Venuſium</hi> woods:</l>
                     <l>And may on eu'ry ſide, thy traffick'd goods,</l>
                     <l>In plentie flow to thee, from <hi>Ioue's</hi> iuſt hand,</l>
                     <l>Aud <hi>Neptune,</hi> who <hi>Tarentum</hi> doth command:</l>
                     <l>But if to fruſtrate me thou bee not nice,</l>
                     <l>Which may thy guiltleſſe iſſue preiudice;</l>
                     <l>I wiſh due puniſhment, and proud neglect,</l>
                     <l>May on thy Funerall Obſcquies reflect:</l>
                     <l>Nor may my Prayers be powred forth in vaine,</l>
                     <l>Nor vowes haue ſtrength to ſet thee free againe.</l>
                     <l>Yet if thou haſt, no longer ſtay I craue,</l>
                     <l>Then, thrice the duſt be throwne vpon my graue.</l>
                  </lg>
               </div>
               <div n="31" type="ode">
                  <pb n="10" facs="tcp:4433:11"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>Ode</hi> XXXI. To APOLLO.</head>
                  <argument>
                     <p>He deſireth not riches of <hi>Apollo,</hi> but that hee may haue a ſound mind in a healthy bodie.</p>
                  </argument>
                  <lg>
                     <head>Quid dedicatum poſcit.</head>
                     <l>WHat doth thy Poet aske <hi>Phaebus</hi> diuine?)</l>
                     <l>What craues he, when he powres thee bowls of wine?</l>
                     <l>Not the rich corne of fat <hi>Sardinia,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Nor gratefull flockes of burnt <hi>Calabria,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Nor Gold, nor <hi>Indian</hi> Iuory; nor the grounds,</l>
                     <l>Which ſilent <hi>Lyris,</hi> with ſoft ſtreame arrounds:</l>
                     <l>Let thoſe whom Fortune ſo much ſtore aſſignes,</l>
                     <l>Dreſſe with <hi>Calenian</hi> hooke, their fertile Vines:</l>
                     <l>Let the rich Merchant to the Gods ſo deare,</l>
                     <l>(For ſo I tearme him right, who euery yeare</l>
                     <l>Three, or foure times, viſits th' <hi>Atlantique</hi> Seas,</l>
                     <l>From ſhipwracke free:) Let him his palate pleaſe,</l>
                     <l>And drinke in gilt bowles, wines of higheſt price,</l>
                     <l>Bought with the ſale of <hi>Syrian</hi> Marchandiſe.</l>
                     <l>Looſe Mallowes, Succory, and Oliue plant</l>
                     <l>Serue me for food. O (great <hi>Apollo)</hi> grant,</l>
                     <l>To me in health, and free from lifes annoy,</l>
                     <l>Things natiue, and ſoone gotten to enioy;</l>
                     <pb n="11" facs="tcp:4433:11"/>
                     <l>And with a mind compoſ'd old age attaine,</l>
                     <l>Not lothſome, nor depriu'd of <hi>Lyrick</hi> ſtraine.</l>
                  </lg>
               </div>
               <div n="34" type="ode">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Ode</hi> XXXIV. To HIMSELFE.</head>
                  <argument>
                     <p>Who repenteth, that hauing followed the <hi>Epicurean</hi> Sect, he therby hath negligently honored the gods.</p>
                  </argument>
                  <lg>
                     <head>Parcus Deorum cultor.</head>
                     <l>I, Of the gods a tardie worſhipper,</l>
                     <l>Whilſt (skill'd) in frantike wiſedome I doe erre,</l>
                     <l>Now backward forced am my ſayles to raiſe,</l>
                     <l>And to ſeeke out againe forſaken wayes.</l>
                     <l>For <hi>Iupiter,</hi> who light to day inſpires,</l>
                     <l>Diuiding ſable clouds, with ſhining fires,</l>
                     <l>Hath through the cleare skie oft ordain'd his drift,</l>
                     <l>With thunder breathing horſe and chariot ſwift,</l>
                     <l>Wherewith d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ll earth, and wandring riuers quake,</l>
                     <l>The <hi>Stygian</hi> Fenne, and horrid Seat doth ſhake</l>
                     <l>Of hatefull <hi>Taenarus,</hi> and <hi>Atlas</hi> bounds.</l>
                     <l>"God, in exchange, the high with low confounds:</l>
                     <l>"Hee abiect baſeneſſe on the higheſt flings,</l>
                     <l>"And caſteth luſtre on obſcured things.</l>
                     <pb n="12" facs="tcp:4433:12"/>
                     <l>Hence reſtleſſe Fortune, height from one man takes,</l>
                     <l>With ſhrilleſt noyſe, and great another makes.</l>
                  </lg>
               </div>
               <div n="35" type="ode">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Ode</hi> XXXV. To FORTVNE.</head>
                  <argument>
                     <p>Hee beſeecheth her, that ſhee would preſerue <hi>Caeſar</hi> going into <hi>Brittany.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </argument>
                  <lg>
                     <head>O diua gratum.</head>
                     <l>O Goddeſſe, which beloued <hi>Antium</hi> ſwayes,</l>
                     <l>Still ready with thy powerfull arme to raiſe,</l>
                     <l>Men from the low degree of wretched thralls,</l>
                     <l>Or turne proud triumphs into funeralls.</l>
                     <l>The poore, and ruſtick Clowne, with humble plea</l>
                     <l>Sollicites thee: Thee Lady of the Sea,</l>
                     <l>Hee lowdly inuocates; who e're doth ſweepe</l>
                     <l>In <hi>Aſian</hi> veſſell the <hi>Carpathian</hi> deepe.</l>
                     <l>The <hi>Dacian</hi> rough, the wandring <hi>Scythian,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Cities, and Kingdomes; The fierce <hi>Latian;</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Thee Mothers of <hi>Barbarian</hi> Kings doe feare,</l>
                     <l>And Tyrants, which bright purple garments weare.</l>
                     <l>Let not a ſtanding pillar bee or'ethrowne</l>
                     <l>With thy offended foot; nor bee it knowne,</l>
                     <pb n="13" facs="tcp:4433:12"/>
                     <l>That people apt for armes, yet now at reſt,</l>
                     <l>Take armes againe, and Empires peace infeſt.</l>
                     <l>Thee ſharpe Neceſſitie, doth ſtill fore-goe,</l>
                     <l>Holding in brazen hand, as pledge of woe,</l>
                     <l>Tormenting beames, and racks: and more to dant,</l>
                     <l>Sharpe hookes, and molten lead doe neuer want.</l>
                     <l>Thee Hope, and ſimple Faith in white attire,</l>
                     <l>Doth honour, and thy company deſire,</l>
                     <l>How e're another habit thou doſt take,</l>
                     <l>And made a foe, great houſes thou forſake.</l>
                     <l>But the falſe multitude, and periur'd whore</l>
                     <l>Doth backe retire; yea friends when veſſells ſtore,</l>
                     <l>Is to the dregges drunke vp; Away they flie,</l>
                     <l>Shunning the yoke of mutuall pouertie.</l>
                     <l>Preſerue thou <hi>Caeſar</hi> ſafe, wee thee implore,</l>
                     <l>Bound to the world's remoteſt <hi>Brittan</hi> ſhore,</l>
                     <l>And the late rayſed troupes of youth moſt able,</l>
                     <l>To Eaſterne parts, and red Sea formidable.</l>
                     <l>We at our ſcarres doe bluſh, Sinne, Brothers fall.</l>
                     <l>(Vile Age) what miſchefes doe we ſhun at all?</l>
                     <l>What youth, his hand, for feare of gods containes?</l>
                     <l>Or who himſelfe from Altars ſpoyle reſtraines?</l>
                     <l>Ah wouldſt thou now our blunted ſwords new frame</l>
                     <l>Th' <hi>Arabians,</hi> and the <hi>Maſſagetes</hi> to tame.</l>
                  </lg>
               </div>
            </div>
            <trailer>The end of the first Booke.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="odes">
            <pb n="14" facs="tcp:4433:13"/>
            <head>ODES OF HORACE.</head>
            <div n="2" type="book">
               <head>The Second Booke.</head>
               <div n="2" type="ode">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Ode.</hi> II. To C. SALVSTIVS CRISPVS.</head>
                  <argument>
                     <p>Hee prayſeth <hi>Proculeius</hi> for liberalitie towards his brothers. Onely contempt of money maketh a man happie.</p>
                  </argument>
                  <lg>
                     <head>Nullus Argento color.</head>
                     <l>NO colour is in Golden vaine,</l>
                     <l>(Oh <hi>Saluſt,</hi> enemy of gaine)</l>
                     <l>Hidden within a greedie Mine,</l>
                     <l>Vnleſſe with temp'rate vſe it ſhine.</l>
                     <l>Neuer ſhall <hi>Proculeius</hi> die,</l>
                     <l>'Mongſt Brothers mark'd for pietie:</l>
                     <pb n="15" facs="tcp:4433:13"/>
                     <l>Suruiuing Fame with daring flight,</l>
                     <l>Shall yeeld his Name eternall right.</l>
                     <l>In larger circuit thou doſt raigne,</l>
                     <l>If greedy humour thou reſtraine.</l>
                     <l>Then if thou <hi>Gades</hi> to <hi>Lybia</hi> ioyne,</l>
                     <l>Or both the <hi>Carthages</hi> were thine.</l>
                     <l>The ſelfe-indulgent Dropſie growes,</l>
                     <l>Nor doth the palate's thirſt vnloſe,</l>
                     <l>Till man from vaines, the ſickneſſe cauſe,</l>
                     <l>And pallid watry faintneſſe drawes.</l>
                     <l>Vertue, that vulgar doth oppoſe,</l>
                     <l>Not in the ranke of happy, choſe</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Phraat</hi> with <hi>Cyrus</hi> throne indu'de.</l>
                     <l>And doth forbid the multitude</l>
                     <l>Falſe acclamations to make;</l>
                     <l>And rule, and Scepter ſafe partake,</l>
                     <l>And Bayes to him alone apply,</l>
                     <l>Who viewes huge heapes with careleſſe eye.</l>
                  </lg>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="ode">
                  <pb n="16" facs="tcp:4433:14"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>Ode</hi> III. To DELIVS.</head>
                  <argument>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Proſperous, and aduerſe Fortune are to be moderate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly borne, ſince one, and the ſelfe ſame condition of death, hangeth ouer euery man.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </argument>
                  <lg>
                     <head>Aequam memento.</head>
                     <l>IN aduerſe chaunce, an equall mind retaine,</l>
                     <l>As in beſt fortunes temp'red, free from vaine</l>
                     <l>Of mirth profuſe: For <hi>(Delius)</hi> thou muſt dy,</l>
                     <l>Whither in ſadneſſe, thou doeſt euer ly;</l>
                     <l>Or, on Feaſt dayes retyr'd to graſſie ſhade,</l>
                     <l>Thou with cloſe <hi>Falerne</hi> wine art happy made:</l>
                     <l>Where the white Poplar, and the loftie Pine,</l>
                     <l>Their friendly ſhade in mutuall branches twine:</l>
                     <l>And Riuers ſwiftly gliding ſtriue, apace</l>
                     <l>'Bout crooked bankes, their trembling ſtreames to chaſe.</l>
                     <l>Bring hither Wine, and od'rous Vnguents. Bring</l>
                     <l>The daintie Roſe, a faire, but fading thing.</l>
                     <l>While Fortune, age, and wealth yeeld ſeaſons fit.</l>
                     <l>And the three Siſters ſable loomes permit:</l>
                     <l>Thou from thy houſe muſt part, &amp; purchas'd woods,</l>
                     <l>And village lau'd, with yellow <hi>Tybers</hi> floods.</l>
                     <l>And thy high hoarded heaps of wealths exceſſe,</l>
                     <l>An Heire (perhaps) vngratefull ſhall poſſeſſe.</l>
                     <pb n="17" facs="tcp:4433:14"/>
                     <l>No matter tis, whither thou rich art borne,</l>
                     <l>Of <hi>Argine</hi> Kings; or low, expos'd to ſcorne,</l>
                     <l>Sprung from poore Parents, liu'ſt in open fields;</l>
                     <l>Thou art Death's ſacrifice, (who neuer yeelds.)</l>
                     <l>Wee all are thither brought, 'tis hee that turnes,</l>
                     <l>And windes our mortall life's vncertaine Vrnes.</l>
                     <l>Sooner or later each man hath his lot,</l>
                     <l>And exil'd hence, embarques in <hi>Charon's</hi> Boat.</l>
                  </lg>
               </div>
               <div n="9" type="ode">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Ode</hi> IX. To VALGIVS.</head>
                  <argument>
                     <p>That now at length hee would deſiſt, to deplore his deceaſed <hi>Myſte.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </argument>
                  <lg>
                     <head>Non ſemper imbres.</head>
                     <l>THe ſwelling cloud, not alwayes powres,</l>
                     <l>On rugged fields impetuous ſhowres.</l>
                     <l>Nor <hi>Caſpian</hi> Sea <hi>(Valgius</hi> belou'd)</l>
                     <l>With toſſing ſtormes, is euer mou'd.</l>
                     <l>Nor on <hi>Armenia's</hi> bord'ring ſhore,</l>
                     <l>The ſluggiſh ice ſtands alwayes hore:</l>
                     <l>Or <hi>Ga<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>gan</hi> groues, with North-winds riu'd,</l>
                     <l>Or Aſh trees are of leaues depriu'd.</l>
                     <l>You ſtill in mournfull ſort complaine</l>
                     <l>That death, hath deareſt <hi>Myste</hi> ſlaine.</l>
                     <pb n="18" facs="tcp:4433:15"/>
                     <l>Your loue not failes, if <hi>Veſper</hi> riſe,</l>
                     <l>Nor when bright <hi>Heſper, Phoebus</hi> flies.</l>
                     <l>But thrice-ag'd <hi>Neſtor,</hi> mourn'd not ſtill,</l>
                     <l>That death <hi>An<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>ilochus</hi> did kill:</l>
                     <l>Nor Parents, nor ſad Siſters, euer</l>
                     <l>To waile young <hi>Troilus</hi> perſeuer.</l>
                     <l>Ceaſe then at length, thy ſoft complaint;</l>
                     <l>And in our Songs, now, let vs paint,</l>
                     <l>Great <hi>Caeſar's</hi> Trophies, and command,</l>
                     <l>And how conioyn'd to conquer'd land,</l>
                     <l>The <hi>Median</hi> ſtreame, and <hi>Nyphate</hi> ſtrong,</l>
                     <l>Doe in leſſe Channells, runne along;</l>
                     <l>And <hi>Gelon's</hi> to leſſe limits ty'de,</l>
                     <l>In farre more aightned fields doe ride.</l>
                  </lg>
               </div>
               <div n="10" type="ode">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Ode</hi> X. To LICINIVS.</head>
                  <argument>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Mediocritie to bee vſed in either Fortunes.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </argument>
                  <lg>
                     <head>Rectius viues Licini.</head>
                     <l>YOur ſafer courſe <hi>(Licinius)</hi> count,</l>
                     <l>Not alwayes on the Maine to mount:</l>
                     <l>Not whilſt you (wiſely) ſtormes abhorre,</l>
                     <l>Too much to truſt the ſhelfie ſhore.</l>
                     <l>Hee that affects the golden meane,</l>
                     <l>Liues ſafe from Cottages vncleane,</l>
                     <pb n="19" facs="tcp:4433:15"/>
                     <l>And (ſober) doth as much deſpiſe,</l>
                     <l>In Enuy breeding Courts to riſe.</l>
                     <l>The bluſtring winds more often farre,</l>
                     <l>Gainſt loftie Pinès, doe threaten warre:</l>
                     <l>Braue Towers with greater ruine fall,</l>
                     <l>And Thunders higheſt hills enthrall,</l>
                     <l>Each Fortune, minds prepar'd doth glad,</l>
                     <l>They feare in good, and hope in bad.</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Ioue</hi> brings in horrid Winters rage,</l>
                     <l>And ſodainly doth it aſſwage.</l>
                     <l>If with thee now, it bee but ill,</l>
                     <l>Thinke that it cannot bee ſo ſtill.</l>
                     <l>Sometimes <hi>Apollo's</hi> ſilent Muſe,</l>
                     <l>Speakes in his Harpe; nor doth he vſe,</l>
                     <l>Alwayes to bend his angry Bow;</l>
                     <l>In croſſes ſtrength, and courage ſhow.</l>
                     <l>And let your ſayles with proſperous wind</l>
                     <l>Too much aduanced, bee declin'd.</l>
                  </lg>
               </div>
               <div n="11" type="ode">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Ode</hi> XI. To QVINTVS HIRPINVS.</head>
                  <argument>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Cares layd aſide, let vs liue merily.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </argument>
                  <lg>
                     <head>Quid bellicoſus Cantaber.</head>
                     <l>VVHat the <hi>Cantabrian</hi> ſtout, or <hi>Scythian</hi> thinke,</l>
                     <l>Diuided with oppoſed <hi>Adria's</hi> brinke,</l>
                     <pb n="20" facs="tcp:4433:16"/>
                     <l>
                        <hi>(Quintus Hirpinus)</hi> doe not thou enquire,</l>
                     <l>Nor for life's vſe, which little doth deſire,</l>
                     <l>Bee thou too carefull. Smooth-fac'd youth, apace</l>
                     <l>Doth backward flie, and with it beautie's grace.</l>
                     <l>Dry aged hoarineſſe with furrowes deepe,</l>
                     <l>Diſpelling amorous fires, and gentle ſleepe.</l>
                     <l>The Summer flowers keepe not their natiue grace,</l>
                     <l>Nor ſhines the bright Moone, with a conſtant face.</l>
                     <l>Why doſt thou tyre thy mind, ſubordinate</l>
                     <l>Vnto the Councells of Eternall Fate?</l>
                     <l>Why vnder this high Plane, or Pine tree's ſhade</l>
                     <l>In diſcompoſed manner, careleſſe layd,</l>
                     <l>Our hoary hayre perfum'd with fragrant Roſe,</l>
                     <l>And odours, which <hi>Aſſyria</hi> doth diſcloſe.</l>
                     <l>Doe we (annoynted) not to drinke prepare?</l>
                     <l>Free <hi>Bacchus</hi> diſſipates conſuming care.</l>
                     <l>But (oh) what Boy, <hi>Falernian</hi> wines hote rage,</l>
                     <l>Will ſoone for me, with gliding ſtreames aſſwage?</l>
                     <l>(Ah) who retyred <hi>Lyde</hi> will require,</l>
                     <l>Hither to come. Boy with her Iuory Lyre,</l>
                     <l>Bid her make haſte, and haire to tie not ſhame,</l>
                     <l>In careleſſe knot, like a <hi>Laconian</hi> Dame.</l>
                  </lg>
               </div>
               <div n="14" type="ode">
                  <pb n="21" facs="tcp:4433:16"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>Ode</hi> XIV. To POSTHVMVS.</head>
                  <argument>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Life is ſhort, and Death is neceſſary.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </argument>
                  <lg>
                     <head>Eheu fugaces Poſthume.</head>
                     <l>AH <hi>Poſthumus,</hi> ſwift yeares doe paſſe,</l>
                     <l>Nor can religious zeale (alas)</l>
                     <l>To wrinckles, or decrepit dayes,</l>
                     <l>Or Death vntamed bring delayes:</l>
                     <l>Not, if thou to harſh <hi>Plutoe's</hi> ſhrine</l>
                     <l>Each day three hundred Bulls aſſigne:</l>
                     <l>Who <hi>Geryon,</hi> and <hi>Tytius</hi> bound,</l>
                     <l>With ſable Riuer, doth ſurround.</l>
                     <l>A ſtreame on which each man muſt ſayle,</l>
                     <l>From royall Scepter to the flayle.</l>
                     <l>Wee bloody <hi>Mars</hi> decline in vaine,</l>
                     <l>Or broken waues of <hi>Adrian</hi> maine:</l>
                     <l>And (needleſſe) feare in Autumne rife,</l>
                     <l>The South-wind's hurtfull to our life.</l>
                     <l>Wandring <hi>Cocytus</hi> Flood, with ſlow</l>
                     <l>And heauy Current, thou muſt know.</l>
                     <l>And <hi>Danâus</hi> infamous traine,</l>
                     <l>And <hi>Syſiphus</hi> with endleſſe paine.</l>
                     <l>Thou Houſe, Land, louely Wife muſt want,</l>
                     <l>Nor of the Trees, which thou doſt plant,</l>
                     <pb n="22" facs="tcp:4433:17"/>
                     <l>(Thou dead) will any wayt on thee,</l>
                     <l>But the deſpiſed Cypreſſe tree.</l>
                     <l>Thy worthier Heire, drinkes precious wine,</l>
                     <l>Which thou with hundred keies did'ſt ſhrine;</l>
                     <l>And with it the rich pauement dewes;</l>
                     <l>None ſuch the high Prieſts Banquet ſhewes.</l>
                  </lg>
               </div>
               <div n="15" type="ode">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Ode.</hi> XV.</head>
                  <argument>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Against the exceſſe of that Age.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </argument>
                  <lg>
                     <head>Iam pauca aratro.</head>
                     <l>MAgnifique buildings will leaue ſhortly, now,</l>
                     <l>Few Akers of firme land, vnto the Plough;</l>
                     <l>Now many are beheld huge Pooles to make</l>
                     <l>Of much more wide extent, then <hi>Lucrine</hi> Lake.</l>
                     <l>The ſolitary Plane, the Elme ſupplants,</l>
                     <l>And now no ſort of od'rous flowers wants,</l>
                     <l>As Roſes, Violets, and <hi>Venus-</hi>Mirtle,</l>
                     <l>Where th'Oliue grew, to former Lords ſo fertile.</l>
                     <l>The Lawrell now, to <hi>Phebus</hi> piercing eye,</l>
                     <l>Through his thick branches paſſage doth denie.</l>
                     <l>No ſuch Praeſcript, did <hi>R<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>mulus</hi> exact,</l>
                     <l>Nor Elders, nor rough <hi>Cato</hi> did enact.</l>
                     <l>Priuate Reuenues, then, were ſhort, and low,</l>
                     <l>And each man ſought to make the publike flow.</l>
                     <l>Proud Galleries no priuate man, then made,</l>
                     <l>Of ten foot wide, to let in Northerne ſhade.</l>
                     <pb n="23" facs="tcp:4433:17"/>
                     <l>Nor did our Lawes, then, ſuffer vs diſdaine,</l>
                     <l>A caſuall Turfe, for Pillow to retaine;</l>
                     <l>Commaunding townes to build, at publique charge,</l>
                     <l>And the gods Temples, with new ſtone enlarge.</l>
                  </lg>
               </div>
               <div n="16" type="ode">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Ode</hi> XVI. TO GROSPHVS.</head>
                  <argument>
                     <p>
                        <hi>All men deſire tranquilitie of mind, which can nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with Riches, nor Honours bee acquired, but onely with bridleling our Appetites.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </argument>
                  <lg>
                     <head>Otium Diuos rogat.</head>
                     <l>SOone as black clouds haue hid the <hi>Moones</hi> bright eye,</l>
                     <l>And Pilots cannot beſt known Stars eſpy,</l>
                     <l>The Marriner toſſ'd in <hi>Aegean</hi> Sea,</l>
                     <l>Straight to the gods for reſt makes humble plea.</l>
                     <l>The <hi>Thracians</hi> fierce in warre doe eaſe require,</l>
                     <l>And Quiuer-bearing <hi>Medes</hi> repoſe deſire,</l>
                     <l>Repoſe, which not with gemms, purple, or gold,</l>
                     <l>(Beleeue me <hi>Groſphus)</hi> will be bought, or ſold.</l>
                     <l>No Wealth, nor Conſulls Lictors that make way,</l>
                     <l>Can from the Heart diſturbed tumults fray,</l>
                     <l>Nor cares which round about gilt roofes doe fly.</l>
                     <l>Hee with a little liueth happily,</l>
                     <l>Who hauing on his homely Table plac'd,</l>
                     <l>His Fathers Cup, and Salt kept vndefac'd,</l>
                     <pb n="24" facs="tcp:4433:18"/>
                     <l>So liues, that feare, nor ſordid lucre keepe</l>
                     <l>His waking eyes from ſoft, and gentle ſleepe.</l>
                     <l>Why doe wee (boldly) many things propoſe</l>
                     <l>In <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>ort liu'd age, which <hi>Time</hi> doth quickly cloſe?</l>
                     <l>Why lands with other Sonne enflamed change?</l>
                     <l>Who from himſelfe, though far fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> home can range?</l>
                     <l>Strong Ships are boarded by conſuming Care:</l>
                     <l>Nor doth ſhe braueſt troupes of Horſemen ſpare:</l>
                     <l>More ſwift ſhee is, then the light footed Hind,</l>
                     <l>Or tempeft-raiſing ſtormes of Eaſterne wind.</l>
                     <l>The mind in preſent cheerefull, hates to care</l>
                     <l>For what beyond it lies; And doth prepare</l>
                     <l>To temper bitter things with laughter free:</l>
                     <l>"Nothing in all reſpects can happy bee.</l>
                     <l>Death quickly ſnatched braue <hi>Achilles</hi> hence,</l>
                     <l>Nor did with <hi>Tython's</hi> long liu'd age diſpenſe:</l>
                     <l>And that (perhaps) of time I may obtaine,</l>
                     <l>Which thy expecting hopes ſhall neuer gaine.</l>
                     <l>You many fertile flocks of ſheepe command,</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Siciliax</hi> Kine about you lowing ſtand.</l>
                     <l>Your Mares for Chariot fit, are heard from farre,</l>
                     <l>Lowdly to neigh: Nor garments wanting are,</l>
                     <l>Of Purple cloth, dipp'd twice in <hi>Affrick</hi> Dy;</l>
                     <l>While a poore ſtate, by vpright deſtiny,</l>
                     <l>To me is giu'n; mix'd with a ſlender name,</l>
                     <l>Of Greekiſh Muſe, and ſcorne of vulgar Fame.</l>
                  </lg>
               </div>
               <div n="17" type="ode">
                  <pb n="25" facs="tcp:4433:18"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>Ode</hi> XVII. TO MAECENAS being ſicke.</head>
                  <argument>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Whom hee reſolueth not to ſur<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>iue.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </argument>
                  <lg>
                     <head>Cur Me querelis.</head>
                     <l>WHy kill you mee with your laments?</l>
                     <l>It neither gods, nor mee contents,</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Macenas</hi> (firſt) ſhould yeeld to Fate,</l>
                     <l>The Grace, and Piller of my State.</l>
                     <l>But if a ſpeedier ſtroke of death,</l>
                     <l>Rob thee (my ſoules beſt part) of breath?</l>
                     <l>Why ſtay I in the other, <hi>Sole,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Not pleaſing to my <hi>Selfe,</hi> nor <hi>whole?</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>One day ſhall ſee vs periſh both:</l>
                     <l>I haue not ſworne an idle oath.</l>
                     <l>Goe, when you pleaſe, I will not ſtay,</l>
                     <l>But be your partner in the way.</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Chimaera's</hi> ſpirit breathing fire,</l>
                     <l>Nor hundred-handed <hi>Gyas,</hi> Ire;</l>
                     <l>Shall this my fixed vow abate;</l>
                     <l>Thus Iuſtice hath it pleas'd, and Fate.</l>
                     <l>Though <hi>Libra</hi> in his full aſpect,</l>
                     <l>And feared-<hi>Scorpius,</hi> direct,</l>
                     <l>My <hi>Horoſcope</hi> with rage infeſt,</l>
                     <l>Or, <hi>Capricorne,</hi> that rules the Weſt;</l>
                     <pb n="26" facs="tcp:4433:19"/>
                     <l>Our Conſtellations both agree</l>
                     <l>In admirable ſort. And thee</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>loues</hi> radiant luſtre, hath exempt,</l>
                     <l>From <hi>Saturnes</hi> Beame maleuolent,</l>
                     <l>And ſlack'd the wings of ſpeedy death,</l>
                     <l>What time the people with lowd breath,</l>
                     <l>Thrice in the Theater did ſound</l>
                     <l>That gladſome newe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>: Eu'n then a wound,</l>
                     <l>By a tree's fall, my skull had broke.</l>
                     <l>But Wood-god <hi>Faunus,</hi> from the ſtroke,</l>
                     <l>Mee then did happily aſſiſt,</l>
                     <l>(Patron of each <hi>Mercurialiſt.)</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Then pay thy vowes, thy Temple build,</l>
                     <l>And I a tender Lambe will yeeld.</l>
                  </lg>
               </div>
               <div n="18" type="ode">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Ode</hi> XVIII.</head>
                  <argument>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Hee affirmeth himſelfe content with little, while o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers are wholly addicted to their deſires, and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe of riches, as if they ſhould alwayes line.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </argument>
                  <lg>
                     <head>Non ebur, neque aureum.</head>
                     <l>No guilded roofe, nor Iuory fret,</l>
                     <l>For ſplendor in my houſe is ſet;</l>
                     <pb n="27" facs="tcp:4433:19"/>
                     <l>Nor beames are from <hi>Hymettia</hi> ſought,</l>
                     <l>To lye athwart rich Columnes, brought</l>
                     <l>From <hi>Affrick;</hi> nor an heyre vnknowne.</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Altalus</hi> wealth, make I mine owne.</l>
                     <l>No honeſt Clyents wiues you ſee,</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Laconian</hi> Purples weaue for mee:</l>
                     <l>A loyall heart, and gentle vaine,</l>
                     <l>Of wit I haue; which doth conſtraine</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Rome's</hi> richeſt men, to ſeeke the loue,</l>
                     <l>Of mee but poore: Nor gods aboue,</l>
                     <l>Doe I inuoke for larger ſtore;</l>
                     <l>Nor of <hi>Macenas</hi> aske I more.</l>
                     <l>To mee, my onely <hi>Sabine</hi> field,</l>
                     <l>Sufficient happineſſe doth yeeld.</l>
                     <l>"One day thruſt's on another faſt,</l>
                     <l>And new Moones to the Wane doe haſt.</l>
                     <l>When death (perhaps) is neare at hand,</l>
                     <l>Thou fayreſt Marbles doſt command</l>
                     <l>Be cut for vſe, yet doſt neglect</l>
                     <l>Thy graue, and houſes ſtill erect,</l>
                     <l>And would'ſt abridge, the vaſt Sea's ſhore,</l>
                     <l>Which loudly doth at <hi>Baia</hi> rore:</l>
                     <l>Enriched little, leſſe content,</l>
                     <l>With limits of the Continent.</l>
                     <l>Why often pull you vp your bounds,</l>
                     <l>T'enlarge the Circuit of your grounds,</l>
                     <l>And greedily your liſt extend</l>
                     <l>Beyond your neighbour ſtraightly penn'd<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </l>
                     <l>Both man, and wife with ſordid brood,</l>
                     <l>And ancient houſhold gods, that ſtood</l>
                     <pb n="28" facs="tcp:4433:20"/>
                     <l>In quiet peace, muſt bee expeld;</l>
                     <l>Yet is no habitation, held,</l>
                     <l>For the rich Land-lord, ſo aſſur'd,</l>
                     <l>As in deepe Hell to bee immur'd.</l>
                     <l>Then whither doe you further tend?</l>
                     <l>Th'indifferent Earth, an equall friend,</l>
                     <l>As willingly opens her wombe,</l>
                     <l>For Beggers graue, as Prince's Tombe.</l>
                     <l>Gold could of <hi>Charon</hi> not obtaine,</l>
                     <l>To beare <hi>Prometheus</hi> backe againe.</l>
                     <l>Proud <hi>Tantalus,</hi> and all his ſtock,</l>
                     <l>Hee, in the bands of <hi>Fate</hi> did lock.</l>
                     <l>And call'd, or not call'd ſtill is preſt,</l>
                     <l>To giue the labouring poore man, Reſt.</l>
                  </lg>
               </div>
            </div>
            <trailer>The end of the ſecond Booke.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="odes">
            <pb n="29" facs="tcp:4433:20"/>
            <head>ODES OF HORACE.</head>
            <div n="3" type="book">
               <head>The Third Booke.</head>
               <div n="1" type="ode">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Ode</hi> I.</head>
                  <argument>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Life is made happy, not with Riches, but Mind's Tranquilitie.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </argument>
                  <lg>
                     <head>Odi profanum vulgus.</head>
                     <l>I Hate, and from mee doe exclude,</l>
                     <l>The moſt illiterate Multitude.</l>
                     <l>You knowing Spirits, fauour bring</l>
                     <l>To me the Muſes Prieſt, who ſing</l>
                     <l>To Boyes, and ſpotleſſe Virgins, Verſe</l>
                     <l>Which none did euer yet reherſe.</l>
                     <l>Kings awfull, their owne Subiects ſway,</l>
                     <l>And Kings themſelues doe <hi>loue</hi> obay:</l>
                     <pb n="30" facs="tcp:4433:21"/>
                     <l>Who famous for the Gyants fall,</l>
                     <l>With brow auſtere doth mannage all.</l>
                     <l>Say one, more large in furrowes plant</l>
                     <l>Trees, which another man doth want.</l>
                     <l>What though one boaſt a nobler ſtraine,</l>
                     <l>Affected honours to attaine:</l>
                     <l>One better life, and Fame pretends,</l>
                     <l>Another hath more troupes of friends:</l>
                     <l>With equall Law, ne're fayling death,</l>
                     <l>The rich, and poore depriues of breath:</l>
                     <l>Caſting that name, from forth his Vrne,</l>
                     <l>Which next by lot to death muſt turne.</l>
                     <l>To him, who o're his wicked head,</l>
                     <l>A drawne ſword ſees in twine of thread,</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Sicilian</hi> Feaſts, with dainties grac't,</l>
                     <l>Procure not Palate-pleaſing taſt;</l>
                     <l>No chant of Birds, nor charme of Lyre,</l>
                     <l>Can to his eyes, ſoft ſleepe inſpire:</l>
                     <l>Delicious Sleepe, no whit diſdaines,</l>
                     <l>The homely Cottages of Swaines:</l>
                     <l>Nor ſhady bankes, nor <hi>Tempe</hi> groue,</l>
                     <l>Where <hi>Zephirus</hi> doth gently roue.</l>
                     <l>Hee who deſires, but what's enough,</l>
                     <l>Feares not the Ocean billowes rough:</l>
                     <l>Nor ſterne <hi>Arcturus</hi> force, that ſets,</l>
                     <l>Nor riſing <hi>Kid,</hi> who ſtormes begets:</l>
                     <l>His Vines, nor ruin'd are with hayle,</l>
                     <l>Nor doe his crops in Harueſt faile:</l>
                     <l>His fields, now blaming water-falls,</l>
                     <l>Now parching Starres, now Winter-thralls.</l>
                     <pb n="31" facs="tcp:4433:21"/>
                     <l>Yea Fiſhes feele the Seas growne ſtraight,</l>
                     <l>With Bulwarks rais'd, of wondrous waight:</l>
                     <l>Heere the Surueyor, with his traine,</l>
                     <l>And Lord himſelfe, fill'd with diſdaine;</l>
                     <l>Of his firme Land's too narrow ring,</l>
                     <l>Building materialls frequent bring:</l>
                     <l>But angry threats, and reſtleſſe Feare,</l>
                     <l>Goe with their Maſter euery where.</l>
                     <l>Black Care, in ſhip, with him abides,</l>
                     <l>And ſits behind him, when hee rides.</l>
                     <l>But if, nor <hi>Phrygian</hi> Columnes, can,</l>
                     <l>Nor vſe of Purples brighter, than</l>
                     <l>Heauens Lights, diſturbed minds content,</l>
                     <l>Nor <hi>Falerne</hi> Vine, nor <hi>Perſian</hi> Sent.</l>
                     <l>Why Pillars proud, ſhould I erect,</l>
                     <l>Or Gall'ry of new Architect?</l>
                     <l>Why ſhould I <hi>Sabine's</hi> Countrey Grange,</l>
                     <l>For much more buſie wealth exchange?</l>
                  </lg>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="ode">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Ode</hi> II. To his FRIENDS.</head>
                  <argument>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Boyes are to bee enured from their tender age, to po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerty, warfare, and painfull Life.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </argument>
                  <lg>
                     <head>Anguſtam amici.</head>
                     <l>LEt able Youth, it ſelfe enure,</l>
                     <l>By warres ſharpe vſe, want to endure.</l>
                     <pb n="32" facs="tcp:4433:22"/>
                     <l>And mounted on his Horſe, with Speare,</l>
                     <l>No whit bold <hi>Parthians</hi> valour feare:</l>
                     <l>Let him expoſed to open ayre,</l>
                     <l>Liue, and attempt, the hard'ſt affaire.</l>
                     <l>Whom wife of Tyrant, vs'd to warre,</l>
                     <l>Viewing, from hoſtile walls afarre;</l>
                     <l>And Mayd for marriage ripe may crie,</l>
                     <l>With ſighes, which from ſad paſſion flie.</l>
                     <l>Oh, that my royall Loue, vntrain'd</l>
                     <l>In martiall feats, would be reſtrain'd,</l>
                     <l>Not to fierce Combats fatall ſtroke,</l>
                     <l>That wrathfull Lyon to prouoke,</l>
                     <l>Whom bloody angers direfull rage,</l>
                     <l>In thickeſt ſlaughters doth engage.</l>
                     <l>"It is a ſweet, and noble gaine,</l>
                     <l>"In Countreys quarrell to be ſlaine.</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Death,</hi> the ſwift flying man purſues</l>
                     <l>With ready ſteps: Nor doth he vſe,</l>
                     <l>To ſpare, from vnauoyded wrack,</l>
                     <l>Youth's ſupple hammes, or fearefull back.</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Vertue</hi> diſdaining baſe neglect,</l>
                     <l>Doth ſhine with taintleſſe honours deckt:</l>
                     <l>Nor takes, or leaues ſhe honour's choyce,</l>
                     <l>To pleaſe the people's ay'ry voyce.</l>
                     <l>Vertue, vnlocking Heau'n to praiſe,</l>
                     <l>Doth dauntleſſe try, denied wayes.</l>
                     <l>Vulgar aſſemblies doth deſpiſe,</l>
                     <l>And leauing Earth, to Heauen flies.</l>
                     <l>Yea, truſty Silence is not barr'd,</l>
                     <l>To haue a merited reward.</l>
                     <pb n="33" facs="tcp:4433:22"/>
                     <l>Hee, who to blab the holy Rites,</l>
                     <l>Of ſecret <hi>Ceres</hi> Phane delights,</l>
                     <l>Vnder the ſame roofe ſhall not bee,</l>
                     <l>Nor in fraile Veſſell ſayle with mee.</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>"Ioue</hi> oft neglected, makes the Iuſt</l>
                     <l>"To ſmart with thoſe are ſtayn'd with luſt;</l>
                     <l>"Seldome Reuenge, with halting pace,</l>
                     <l>Leaues bad fore-going men to trace.</l>
                  </lg>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="ode">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Ode.</hi> III.</head>
                  <argument>
                     <p>
                        <hi>A man with vertue adorned, feareth nothing.</hi> Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>no's <hi>Oration of</hi> Troye's <hi>ouerthrow, and the end of that warre. And how the Romane Empire ſhall take beginning from the</hi> Troians.</p>
                  </argument>
                  <lg>
                     <head>Iustum &amp; tenacem.</head>
                     <l>HEe, that is iuſt, and of reſolued mind,</l>
                     <l>No voyce of Citizens to bad enclind,</l>
                     <l>Nor angry brow of haſtie Tyrants threat,</l>
                     <l>Can ſhake his ſolid thoughts from Vertue's ſeat.</l>
                     <l>Not the South winde, which doth rough <hi>Adria</hi> ſtirr,</l>
                     <l>Nor potent hand of thundring <hi>Iupiter;</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Yea, ſhould the world diſſolued periſh quite,</l>
                     <l>The ſo <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>aine ruines would him not affright.</l>
                     <pb n="34" facs="tcp:4433:23"/>
                     <l>With this ſame Art, the wandring <hi>Hercules,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>And <hi>Pollux,</hi> did the fi'ry Turrets ſeaze.</l>
                     <l>Twixt whom <hi>Auguſtus</hi> plac'd, with roſie lips</l>
                     <l>Nectar, the Gods eternall liquor, ſips.</l>
                     <l>With this god <hi>Bacchus,</hi> high his worth did reare,</l>
                     <l>By Tygers drawne, vntaught the yoke to beare.</l>
                     <l>With this Art <hi>Romulus</hi> on <hi>Mars</hi> his Steeds,</l>
                     <l>Leaues <hi>Acheron,</hi> and to Heau'ns glory ſpeeds.</l>
                     <l>What time the gods conſulting. <hi>Iuno</hi> ſayd</l>
                     <l>In gratefull accents this; <hi>Troy, Troy,</hi> betray'd,</l>
                     <l>A fatall, and inceſtuous Iudge hath burn'd,</l>
                     <l>And a ſtrange woman vnto Aſhes turn'd.</l>
                     <l>Eu'n from that time, that <hi>Priams</hi> wayward Sire,</l>
                     <l>Bereft the righteous gods their promis'd hire,</l>
                     <l>Which <hi>Troy</hi> by mee, and <hi>Pallas</hi> once contemn'd,</l>
                     <l>With Prince and people, were to flames condemn'd.</l>
                     <l>Now the knowne gueſt, of that adult'rous Dame</l>
                     <l>Which fled from <hi>Greece,</hi> no more ſhall merit fame;</l>
                     <l>And <hi>Priams</hi> periur'd ſtock, with <hi>Hector's</hi> ayd,</l>
                     <l>No more ſhall make the warlike <hi>Greekes</hi> diſmayd.</l>
                     <l>The fatall warres, which our ſeditions fed,</l>
                     <l>Are now compos'd, and angry ſtormes are dead.</l>
                     <l>Henceforth to <hi>Mars</hi> my fury will I leaue,</l>
                     <l>And <hi>Veſta's</hi> off-ſpring vnto grace receiue:</l>
                     <l>Him I to Heau'ns bright manſions will admit,</l>
                     <l>To drinke of <hi>Nectar,</hi> and with gods to ſit:</l>
                     <l>While the vaſt Sea, twixt <hi>Troy,</hi> and <hi>Rome</hi> is found,</l>
                     <l>Raigne happy baniſh'd men on any ground:</l>
                     <l>Whilſt heards o're <hi>Priam's</hi> tombe, and <hi>Paris</hi> ſtray,</l>
                     <l>And beaſts preſerue their young from hunters pray,</l>
                     <pb n="35" facs="tcp:4433:23"/>
                     <l>Let the bright Capitoll it's glory ſpread,</l>
                     <l>And <hi>Rome</hi> giue Lawes vnto the conquer'd <hi>Mead.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Yea let her, her far-dreaded name extend,</l>
                     <l>And with the Earth's remoteſt confines end:</l>
                     <l>Where the Mid-ſtream, <hi>Europe</hi> from <hi>Affrick</hi> bounds,</l>
                     <l>Or ſwelling <hi>Nilus,</hi> watreth fertile grounds.</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Rome</hi> abler farre, to ſcorne gold, yet vnfound,</l>
                     <l>(Which beſt is plac'd, when deepeſt vnder ground,)</l>
                     <l>Then to extract it thence for humane vſe,</l>
                     <l>Each hand things ſacred foyling with abuſe.</l>
                     <l>What limit of the world, ſo e're contend,</l>
                     <l>Let thither <hi>Rome,</hi> her armes victorious ſend.</l>
                     <l>Glad to behold, where the burnt <hi>Zones</hi> doe ſtand,</l>
                     <l>Or clowdy <hi>Poles,</hi> which ſhowry dewes command.</l>
                     <l>But to the moſt vnvanquiſh'd <hi>Romane</hi> State,</l>
                     <l>On this condition I preſcribe this Fate,</l>
                     <l>Leſt they, too pious, and indulgent yeeld,</l>
                     <l>The ruin'd walls of ancient <hi>Troy</hi> to build.</l>
                     <l>Yet if that <hi>Fortune</hi> by vnhappy chance,</l>
                     <l>Should once againe decayed <hi>Troy</hi> aduance,</l>
                     <l>I Wife, and Siſter of <hi>loue,</hi> Heauens King,</l>
                     <l>With armed troupes, would new deſtruction bring.</l>
                     <l>If thrice a Brazen wall, by <hi>Phebus</hi> hand</l>
                     <l>Should reared bee, it thrice by my command,</l>
                     <l>The Greeks ſhould raze, and thrice the captiue wife</l>
                     <l>Her child, and husband mourne, depriu'd of life.</l>
                     <l>But theſe things nothing fit, my ſportiue Lyre;</l>
                     <l>Muſe whither go'ſt thou? Ah! doe not aſpire,</l>
                     <l>The gods diſcourſe, thus boldly to relate,</l>
                     <l>Or great things with low Layes extenuate.</l>
                  </lg>
               </div>
               <div n="6" type="ode">
                  <pb n="36" facs="tcp:4433:24"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>Ode</hi> VI. To The ROMANS.</head>
                  <argument>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Of the corrupt manners of that Age.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </argument>
                  <lg>
                     <head>Delicta maiorum.</head>
                     <l>
                        <hi>(Romane)</hi> reſolue, thou ſhalt deſertleſſe taſt,</l>
                     <l>Sinn's ſcourge, for vice of Predeceſſor paſt,</l>
                     <l>Vntill thou doſt againe, repaire</l>
                     <l>Decayed Temples, and make fayre,</l>
                     <l>The falling houſes of the gods, diſgrac'd,</l>
                     <l>And cleanſe their Images, with ſmoke defac'd.</l>
                     <l>To think thee leſſe then Gods, thy power commends;</l>
                     <l>Hence take beginnings, hither ayme thy ends.</l>
                     <l>The Gods neglected, did impoſe</l>
                     <l>On ſad <hi>Heſperia</hi> many woes.</l>
                     <l>Twice <hi>Pacorus,</hi> and twice <hi>Monaeſes</hi> hand,</l>
                     <l>Our inauſpicious forces did disband:</l>
                     <l>Who with a plenteous prey made glad,</l>
                     <l>To little chaines new links did add.</l>
                     <l>The <hi>Dacian,</hi> and the <hi>Aethiop</hi> fierce in warres,</l>
                     <l>Hath almoſt raz'd the Citie, rent with iarres.</l>
                     <l>One with his Nauy formidable,</l>
                     <l>With Darts, the other better able.</l>
                     <l>This <hi>Age</hi> in Vice abounding, did begin,</l>
                     <l>Chaſt Stocks, and Nuptials to pollute with ſinne:</l>
                     <l>The woes which from this fountaine flow,</l>
                     <l>People, and Countrey ouerthrow.</l>
                     <pb n="37" facs="tcp:4433:24"/>
                     <l>The Mayd for Mariage ripe, much ioyes to learne,</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Ionick</hi> Daunces, and can well diſcerne,</l>
                     <l>With art to faine, and quickly proue,</l>
                     <l>The pleaſures of vnlawfull loue.</l>
                     <l>Straight made a wife in midſt of husband's cups,</l>
                     <l>Shee with young Gallants, and adulterers ſups.</l>
                     <l>Nor doth ſhe care, to whom by ſtealth,</l>
                     <l>(Light's out) ſhe yeeld loues lawleſſe wealth.</l>
                     <l>But ask'd, doth riſe, (her knowing husband by)</l>
                     <l>To proſtitute her Marriage modeſtie:</l>
                     <l>At Factors call, or Pilot's hyre,</l>
                     <l>Of luſtfull ſhame, a coſtly buyer.</l>
                     <l>That youth came not, from ſuch Forefathers ſtraine,</l>
                     <l>Who did the Sea with Punick blood diſtaine.</l>
                     <l>By ſuch hands, <hi>Pyrrhus</hi> did not fall.</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Antiochus,</hi> nor <hi>Hanniball.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>But in thoſe dayes, a braue and manly race</l>
                     <l>Of ruſtick Souldiers liued in this place,</l>
                     <l>Well skill'd in Plough, and <hi>Sabine</hi> ſpade,</l>
                     <l>And ſo to ſtrict obedience made.</l>
                     <l>That if ſharpe mothers bad, at home returne,</l>
                     <l>They on their ſholders brought logs new'd to burne:</l>
                     <l>Soone, as the Sun, did change the mountaines ſhade.</l>
                     <l>And weary vnyoak'd Oxen home-ward made,</l>
                     <l>Night gaue their labours free diſpenſe,</l>
                     <l>Chaſing the Sun's bright Chariot hence.</l>
                     <l>"What waſteth not with <hi>Times</hi> deuouring rage?</l>
                     <l>"Our Fathers life, much worſe the Grandſire's age,</l>
                     <l>"Sees vs more wicked, to produce</l>
                     <l>"An off ſpring fuller of abuſe.</l>
                  </lg>
               </div>
               <div n="9" type="ode">
                  <pb n="38" facs="tcp:4433:25"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>Ode</hi> IX. To LYDIA.</head>
                  <argument>
                     <p>
                        <hi>A Dialogue of his paſſed Loues, and renewing of them againe.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </argument>
                  <p>This Ode, though leſſe morall then the reſt, I haue admitted, for <hi>Iul. Scaliger's</hi> ſake, who much ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mireth it.</p>
                  <lg>
                     <head>Donec gratus eram.</head>
                     <lg>
                        <head>Horace.</head>
                        <l>WHilſt I was pleaſing in thy ey,</l>
                        <l>Nor any to thy heart more nigh,</l>
                        <l>Claſp'd, that white neck in amorous Ring,</l>
                        <l>More bleſſ'd I liu'd, then <hi>Perſia's</hi> King.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <head>Lydia.</head>
                        <l>Whilſt you no other Fire embrac'd,</l>
                        <l>Nor <hi>Chlo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e</hi> before <hi>Lydia</hi> plac'd.</l>
                        <l>I <hi>Lydia</hi> then with honour ſign'd,</l>
                        <l>More then the <hi>Roman Illia</hi> ſhin'd.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <head>Horace.</head>
                        <l>Now <hi>Thracian Chlo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e</hi> I obey,</l>
                        <l>Skillfull, and prompt in Muſick's lay:</l>
                        <l>For whom I will not feare to dy,</l>
                        <l>So Fate to her the ſame deny.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <head>Lydia.</head>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Calais Ornithus</hi> ſonne doth fire</l>
                        <pb n="39" facs="tcp:4433:25"/>
                        <l>My heart with flames of like deſire.</l>
                        <l>For whom I twice to die, will dare</l>
                        <l>So Fates, the youth ſuruiuing ſpare.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <head>Horace.</head>
                        <l>But what if ancient Loue returne,</l>
                        <l>And vs with mutuall paſſion burne;</l>
                        <l>If I ſhake off bright <hi>Chlôe's</hi> hope,</l>
                        <l>And doores to ſcorned <hi>Lydia</hi> ope?</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <head>Lydia.</head>
                        <l>Though hee bee brighter then a Starre,</l>
                        <l>And lighter thou, then Corke by farre.</l>
                        <l>More angry, then rough <hi>Adria;</hi> I</l>
                        <l>With thee would liue, with thee would die.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </lg>
               </div>
               <div n="14" type="ode">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Ode</hi> XIV. To the ROMAN PEOPLE.</head>
                  <argument>
                     <p>
                        <hi>This Ode containeth the prayſes of</hi> Auguſtus <hi>retur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning out of</hi> Spaine, <hi>after his Conqueſt ouer the</hi> Cantabrians.</p>
                  </argument>
                  <lg>
                     <head>Herculis ritu.</head>
                     <l>AS <hi>Hercules,</hi> ſometime was thought</l>
                     <l>Bayes with life's hazard to haue ſought;</l>
                     <l>So <hi>Caeſar</hi> now, to vs reſtores,</l>
                     <l>Our houſhold gods from <hi>Spaniſh</hi> ſhores.</l>
                     <l>The wife that's with one husband pleas'd,</l>
                     <l>Let her come foorth, the gods appeas'd.</l>
                     <pb n="40" facs="tcp:4433:26"/>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Octauia Caeſar's</hi> Siſter, haſt,</l>
                     <l>And Head with humble veyle embrac't,</l>
                     <l>Now Mothers with your Virgins deare,</l>
                     <l>And ſonnes (late) ſafe return'd, appeare.</l>
                     <l>Now Boyes, and you new maryed trayne</l>
                     <l>Of wiues, from euill words abſtaine.</l>
                     <l>From mee this new made Holy-day,</l>
                     <l>Black ſullen cares, ſhall take away.</l>
                     <l>Nor feare I in great <hi>Caeſars</hi> raigne,</l>
                     <l>By force, or tumult to bee ſlaine.</l>
                     <l>(Boy) Crownes, and Vnguents now prepare,</l>
                     <l>And veſſell kept, ſince <hi>Marſian</hi> warre:</l>
                     <l>If any ſuch conceal'd hath been,</l>
                     <l>By wandring <hi>Spartacus</hi> not ſeene.</l>
                     <l>Let ſhrill <hi>Neaera</hi> heere bee found,</l>
                     <l>With golden hayre in treſſes bound.</l>
                     <l>But if the Porter, make delay</l>
                     <l>With churliſh anſwere; Haſt away.</l>
                     <l>White hayres doe mollifie my mind,</l>
                     <l>To brawles, and quarrells earſt inclin'd.</l>
                     <l>This in Youths heat, I could not brooke,</l>
                     <l>When Conſull <hi>Plancus,</hi> Office tooke.</l>
                  </lg>
               </div>
               <div n="16" type="ode">
                  <pb n="41" facs="tcp:4433:26"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>Ode</hi> XVI. To MAECENAS.</head>
                  <argument>
                     <p>
                        <hi>All things lye open to Gold, but</hi> Horace <hi>is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent with his owne Fortune, whereby bee is made happy.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </argument>
                  <lg>
                     <head>Incluſam Danäen.</head>
                     <l>DOores ſtrongly fenced, and a <hi>Brazen Tower,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>With carefull Gard of waking dogs had power</l>
                     <l>Fayre <hi>Dana<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>
                        </hi> in ſtony walls immur'd,</l>
                     <l>From night-Adulterers to haue ſecur'd:</l>
                     <l>Did not both <hi>loue</hi> and <hi>Venus</hi> then deride</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Acriſius,</hi> who the Mayd with feare did hide.</l>
                     <l>For they the way knew free, and ſafe the hold,</l>
                     <l>Were but the god once turned into gold.</l>
                     <l>Gold abler, armed troupes to paſſe, then thunder,</l>
                     <l>The ſtrongeſt Fortreſſes doth rent aſſunder.</l>
                     <l>The <hi>Argiue Angur's</hi> houſe, with all his State,</l>
                     <l>Deſire of gaine did wholly ruinate.</l>
                     <l>With gifts the <hi>Macedonian</hi> did ſubdue,</l>
                     <l>Strong Citie gates, and proud Kings ouerthrew.</l>
                     <l>Sea-men are ſnar'd with gifts, and golden ſtore;</l>
                     <l>"Care, growing wealth purſues with thirſt of more.</l>
                     <pb n="42" facs="tcp:4433:27"/>
                     <l>Then (deare <hi>Maecenas)</hi> well may I deteſt,</l>
                     <l>To vaunt my ſelfe with eleuated creſt.</l>
                     <l>"How much the more, man doth himſelfe deny,</l>
                     <l>"So much the more, the gods will him ſupply.</l>
                     <l>I poore in ſtate, ſeeke thoſe that nought deſire,</l>
                     <l>And, flying, doe from rich mens tents retire,</l>
                     <l>And better liue, Lord of a ſlender ſtore,</l>
                     <l>Then, were I ſayed to hold vpon my flore,</l>
                     <l>What the <hi>Apulian</hi> painfully hath till'd,</l>
                     <l>And in great wealth bee poore, and neuer fill'd.</l>
                     <l>My ſtreame of waters pure, my little Copps;</l>
                     <l>My certaine hope of happy fruitfull crops,</l>
                     <l>From him his hidden in my better chance,</l>
                     <l>Who Empire in rich <hi>Affrick</hi> doth aduance.</l>
                     <l>Though mee <hi>Calabrian</hi> Bees, no Honey giue,</l>
                     <l>Nor wines in <hi>Laeſtrigonian</hi> Flaggons, liue</l>
                     <l>Till age make good the taſt, though no man knowes</l>
                     <l>That my rich fleece in fertile <hi>Gallia</hi> growes.</l>
                     <l>Yet from me, crauing pouertie doth flie;</l>
                     <l>Nor ſhould I aske you more, will you denie.</l>
                     <l>I, better will with limitted deſire,</l>
                     <l>Pay <hi>Caeſar</hi> little tributes, then aſpire</l>
                     <l>By greatneſſe, to vnite the <hi>Phrygian</hi> plaine,</l>
                     <l>To <hi>Alliatts</hi> ample ſtate, and royall raigne.</l>
                     <l>"Who much deſire, want much: He richly liues</l>
                     <l>"Whom God, with ſparing hand ſufficient giues.</l>
                  </lg>
               </div>
               <div n="24" type="ode">
                  <pb n="43" facs="tcp:4433:27"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>Ode</hi> XXIV.</head>
                  <argument>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Againſt couetous rich men.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </argument>
                  <lg>
                     <head>Intactis opulentior.</head>
                     <l>ALthough you richer bee by farre,</l>
                     <l>Then th' <hi>Arabs</hi> Mines vntouch'd, or <hi>Indies</hi> are:</l>
                     <l>Though you with deepe pyles, land would gaine,</l>
                     <l>Eu'n from the <hi>Tyrrhene,</hi> and large <hi>Pontique</hi> Maine.</l>
                     <l>If, on your head ſad <hi>Fate</hi> preuayles,</l>
                     <l>Transfixing it with Adamantine nayles,</l>
                     <l>Yet can you not your mind ſet free,</l>
                     <l>Or life, from ſnares of death exempted ſee.</l>
                     <l>The ſauage <hi>Scithyans</hi> better liue,</l>
                     <l>(Who in their Carts, vnconſtant dwelling driue)</l>
                     <l>And rigid <hi>Getes,</hi> whoſe common ground</l>
                     <l>Doth in full ſtore of Corne and Fruits abound.</l>
                     <l>And loue their tillage to extend,</l>
                     <l>No longer, then the yearely ſeaſon's end:</l>
                     <l>So as, whilſt one man weary lies,</l>
                     <l>A Subſtitute, him with like paines ſupplies.</l>
                     <l>The Step-dame, there, in peacefull aw,</l>
                     <l>Commands her mother-wanting ſonne in law:</l>
                     <l>Nor wife, though rich, her husband ſwayes,</l>
                     <l>Or, to Adult'rer ſpruce, her ſelfe betrayes.</l>
                     <l>"Vertue of Parents, is great Dower,</l>
                     <l>"And Chaſtitie reſtrain'd to Wedlocks power,</l>
                     <pb n="44" facs="tcp:4433:28"/>
                     <l>"Fearefull of others touch; that knowes</l>
                     <l>"The breach is ſinne, and Death the payment owes.</l>
                     <l>Oh, hee that would quite take away</l>
                     <l>All impious ſlaughters, and each ciuill fray:</l>
                     <l>If hee the Citie's Father, care</l>
                     <l>On ſtatues to be ſtil'd: Ah! let him dare,</l>
                     <l>(So ſhall hee future glory gaine)</l>
                     <l>Looſe libertie with bridle to reſtraine.</l>
                     <l>But vertue (liuing) we deſpiſe,</l>
                     <l>And much admire it, taken from our eyes.</l>
                     <l>But what need ſad complaints bee ſpent,</l>
                     <l>If vice be not cut off with puniſhment?</l>
                     <l>What profit Lawes, in vaine compoſ'd,</l>
                     <l>Without good liues? If neither Climes expos'd,</l>
                     <l>To parched heates: Nor Northren ſtarre,</l>
                     <l>Nor ſnow hard cruſted, can the Merchant ſcarre:</l>
                     <l>Wife Marriners, through rough Seas flie,</l>
                     <l>The greateſt imputation <hi>(Pouertie)</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Bids vs doe that, or ſuffer this,</l>
                     <l>Yet doth the painfull way of Vertue miſſe.</l>
                     <l>Then goe wee to the Capitall,</l>
                     <l>Where vulgar voyce, and troupes of friends do call:</l>
                     <l>Or, in the neareſt Sea bee bold,</l>
                     <l>Our gemms, and precious ſtones, with fruitleſſe gold,</l>
                     <l>The root of many ills to caſt.</l>
                     <l>If thou wilt fully ſinnes repentance taſt,</l>
                     <l>Let this firſt ſcope thy thoughts inſpire,</l>
                     <l>To raze the Elements of foule deſire:</l>
                     <l>And in minds tender, apt to ill,</l>
                     <l>To ſeeke the ſharpeſt ſtudies to inſtill:</l>
                     <pb n="45" facs="tcp:4433:28"/>
                     <l>Youth nobly borde, as yet vn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>ide,</l>
                     <l>Feares hunting ſport, and ſpeedy horſe to ride:</l>
                     <l>Farre better skill'd <hi>Greeke Tops</hi> to ply,</l>
                     <l>Or <hi>Dice,</hi> which ancient <hi>Romane</hi> Lawes deny:</l>
                     <l>Whilſt his falſe Syre, with cunning wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>es,</l>
                     <l>His fellow-neighbour, and his gueſt beguiles,</l>
                     <l>And all this, that hee may prepare</l>
                     <l>Great heapes of riches, for his worthleſſe heyre.</l>
                     <l>"Thus, though vile riches grow: yet will</l>
                     <l>"Somewhat to our weake ſtate, be wanting ſtill.</l>
                  </lg>
               </div>
               <div n="28" type="ode">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Ode</hi> XXVIII. To LYDE.</head>
                  <argument>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Hee perſwadeth</hi> Lyde, <hi>to ſpend the day dedicated to</hi> Nep<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="4 letters">
                           <desc>••••</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <hi>
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                              <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                           </gap>
                        </hi>
                     </p>
                  </argument>
                  <lg>
                     <head>Feſto quid potius die.</head>
                     <l>WHat doe we elſe on <hi>Neptune's</hi> Feaſt?</l>
                     <l>Bee therefore <hi>(Lyde)</hi> ready preſt,</l>
                     <l>To broach <hi>Caecubian</hi> Wines, enclos'd;</l>
                     <l>And let ſtrong wiſedome bee oppos'd.</l>
                     <l>Thou ſeeſt, 'its mid-time of the day,</l>
                     <l>And yet, as if ſwi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>t time did ſtay,</l>
                     <pb n="46" facs="tcp:4433:29"/>
                     <l>A Butt, thou ſpar'ſt, was Cellar-ſtalld,</l>
                     <l>When <hi>Bibulus</hi> was Conſull call'd.</l>
                     <l>With mutuall Songs, weele <hi>Neptune</hi> pleaſe,</l>
                     <l>And the greene-hayrd <hi>Neretdes.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>On crooked <hi>Lyre,</hi> ſing thou with art,</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Latona,</hi> and ſwift <hi>Cynthia's</hi> dart:</l>
                     <l>Whilſt our laſt ſtraine, her praiſe vnfolds,</l>
                     <l>Who <hi>Cn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>dos,</hi> and bright <hi>Cyclads</hi> holds:</l>
                     <l>And <hi>Paphos</hi> with payrd Swans doth view;</l>
                     <l>Yet (Night) weele pay th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>e Verſes due.</l>
                  </lg>
               </div>
               <div n="29" type="ode">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Ode</hi> XXIX. To MAECENAS.</head>
                  <argument>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Hee inviteth him to a merry Supper, laying pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liques cares aſide.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </argument>
                  <lg>
                     <head>Tyrrhena regum.</head>
                     <l>OH my <hi>Maecenas,</hi> ſprung from roy I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ſtraine,</l>
                     <l>Of <hi>Tyrrhene</hi> Kings; Behold, I doe retaine,</l>
                     <l>Long ſince by mee reſerued, to be thine,</l>
                     <l>A veſſell, yet vnbroach'd of milder wine;</l>
                     <l>Soft roſie flowers, for thee I will prepare,</l>
                     <l>And ſupple Vnguents, preſſed for thy haire.</l>
                     <l>Then free thee from delay: Nor alwayes yeeld,</l>
                     <l>To view from farre <hi>Aeſulus</hi> hanging field,</l>
                     <pb n="47" facs="tcp:4433:29"/>
                     <l>Moyſt <hi>Tybur's</hi> Site: Nor let thy eyes abide,</l>
                     <l>On hills of <hi>Telegon,</hi> the Particide.</l>
                     <l>Leaue off to ſee, ſucceſſefull <hi>Rome</hi> reioyce,</l>
                     <l>In ſmoaky hopes, much wealth, and vulgar voyce.</l>
                     <l>To great men, changes oft times gratefull are:</l>
                     <l>And vnder humble roofes, neat ſrugall fare,</l>
                     <l>Without rich hangings, or gay purple ſtate,</l>
                     <l>Doth the moſt buſie brow to mirth dilate.</l>
                     <l>Now bright <hi>Andromeda's</hi> refulgent Sire,</l>
                     <l>Shewes to this vnder-world, his hidden fire:</l>
                     <l>Now <hi>Procyon,</hi> and the raging <hi>Lyon</hi> ſwayes,</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Phaebus</hi> reducing drie, and parched dayes.</l>
                     <l>The Shepheard tyr'd, with his faint flock doth hie,</l>
                     <l>To find cook ſhades, or trembling current nigh,</l>
                     <l>And rough <hi>Syluanus</hi> thickets: while the ſhore,</l>
                     <l>Becalmed ſtands, from wind's tumukuons rore.</l>
                     <l>Meane time the good of <hi>Rome,</hi> in mind you beare,</l>
                     <l>And of her much ſollicitous, doe feare</l>
                     <l>What <hi>Seres</hi> plot, or <hi>Bactria Cyrus</hi> ſtate,</l>
                     <l>Or, <hi>Tanais</hi> war like-dweller perpetrate.</l>
                     <l>All-knowing god, with cloudy night doth close</l>
                     <l>Euents of future times, and laughs at thoſe,</l>
                     <l>Who beyond reaſon feare: Thy preſent ſtate,</l>
                     <l>See then with equall mind thou moderate.</l>
                     <l>All other things, like to a Riuer's ſource,</l>
                     <l>Who in the middle Ch<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>nnell of his courſe,</l>
                     <l>Now to the <hi>Tyrrhene</hi> Sea in ſilence ſtrayes;</l>
                     <l>But when fierce Deluges, calme Riuers raiſe,</l>
                     <l>Hee then in heaps rowles down with dreadfull ſound</l>
                     <l>Stones billow-gnawn, &amp; trees torne from the grou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d.</l>
                     <pb n="48" facs="tcp:4433:30"/>
                     <l>With houſe, and cattell borne along the flood,</l>
                     <l>Frighting the hill with noyſe, &amp; neighbouring wood.</l>
                     <l>Hee Maſter of himſelfe, liues merry dayes,</l>
                     <l>Who (this day I haue liu'd) and truely, ſayes;</l>
                     <l>To morrow <hi>(Ioue)</hi> with black clouds heau'n embrace,</l>
                     <l>Or let the Sunne ſhew forth his golden face.</l>
                     <l>Yet notwithſtanding God will not agree,</l>
                     <l>That what is paſſed once, ſhall fruſtrate bee:</l>
                     <l>Nor what the once ſwift-ſliding houre hath wrought,</l>
                     <l>Will he vnfaſhion'd leaue, or bring to nought.</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Fortune</hi> in aduerſe chances, ſportiue euer,</l>
                     <l>And bold in ſcornfull paſtime to perſeuer,</l>
                     <l>Transferreth he<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> vncertaine honours: Now</l>
                     <l>To mee propitious, inſtantly to you.</l>
                     <l>I praiſe her, while ſhee ſtayes, but if ſhee ſhake</l>
                     <l>Her fleet wings, I reſtore what I did take:</l>
                     <l>And mee with my owne vertue, doe inveſt,</l>
                     <l>Making thin honeſt pouertie my gueſt.</l>
                     <l>Tis not for mee, inprayer time to waſt,</l>
                     <l>When wracking, Southerne <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ind hath rent the Maſt,</l>
                     <l>And bargaine with the gods, that the vaſt floods,</l>
                     <l>May to their wealth, not add my <hi>Tyrian</hi> goods:</l>
                     <l>When I, into ſuch dangerous hazard fall,</l>
                     <l>The Wind, and <hi>
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                              <desc>••</desc>
                           </gap>ll<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="3 letters">
                              <desc>•••</desc>
                           </gap>
                        </hi> with his brother, ſhall</l>
                     <l>Mee with a poore two-oated Veſſells ayd,</l>
                     <l>See, ſafely through <hi>Aegtian</hi> ſtor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>es conuayd.</l>
                  </lg>
               </div>
               <div n="30" type="ode">
                  <pb n="49" facs="tcp:4433:30"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>Ode</hi> XXX. To MELPOMENE.</head>
                  <argument>
                     <p>Horace <hi>hath obtained eternall glory, by writing of</hi> Lyrick <hi>Verſes.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </argument>
                  <lg>
                     <head>Exegi Monumentum.</head>
                     <l>A Monument by mee is brought to paſſe,</l>
                     <l>Out-liuing Pyramids, or laſting braſſe,</l>
                     <l>The Sepulchre of Kings; which eating raine,</l>
                     <l>Nor the fierce Northren tempeſt can reſtraine:</l>
                     <l>Nor <hi>Yeares</hi> (though numberleſſe:) nor <hi>Times</hi> ſwift ſtart.</l>
                     <l>I will not wholly die; my better part,</l>
                     <l>Shall ſcape the ſullen hearſe: Bright Fame ſhall raiſe</l>
                     <l>My memory renew'd, with future praiſe:</l>
                     <l>While in the Capitoll the Prieſt aſcends,</l>
                     <l>With <hi>Veſtalls</hi> pure, whom ſilence ſo commends.</l>
                     <l>I (though) of humble ſtraine will be declar'd,</l>
                     <l>The firſt, and able moſt, that euer dar'd,</l>
                     <l>Vnto <hi>Italian</hi> Proportion's vſe,</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Aecolian</hi> antique Meaſures to reduce.</l>
                     <l>Where <hi>Aufidus</hi> with wrathfull ſtreame doth rore,</l>
                     <l>Or <hi>Daunus</hi> poore in waters, reigneth o're</l>
                     <l>Rough barbarous Nations. Take to thee a name,</l>
                     <l>Which beſt <hi>(Melpomene)</hi> may ſute thy fame.</l>
                     <l>And (willingly) thy Poet doth requeſt,</l>
                     <l>My haire with <hi>Delphick</hi> Lawrell thou inueſt.</l>
                  </lg>
               </div>
            </div>
            <trailer>The End of the third Booke.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="odes">
            <pb n="50" facs="tcp:4433:31"/>
            <head>ODES OF HORACE.</head>
            <div n="4" type="book">
               <head>The Fourth Booke.</head>
               <div n="3" type="ode">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Ode</hi> III. To MELPOMENE.</head>
                  <argument>
                     <p>Horace <hi>is borne to Poetry, by whoſe ayd, hee hath obtained immortall glory.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </argument>
                  <lg>
                     <head>Quem tu Melpomene.</head>
                     <l>ON whom <hi>(Melpomene)</hi> with mild aspect,</l>
                     <l>Thou ſhalt thy fauour at his Birth reflect,</l>
                     <l>Him; <hi>Iſtmian</hi> Labour ſhall not higher reare</l>
                     <l>With Wraſtlers title, nor ſwift horſes beare</l>
                     <l>By <hi>Grecian</hi> Chariot drawne, for Victors mee'd</l>
                     <l>In pompous triumph; nor for warlike deed,</l>
                     <l>A Captaine in the Capitoll bee made,</l>
                     <l>And deck'd with <hi>Delian</hi> Bayes, who durſt inuade,</l>
                     <pb n="51" facs="tcp:4433:31"/>
                     <l>And breake the ſwelling threats of hoſtile Kings:</l>
                     <l>But rather thoſe ſoft-falling gentle Springs,</l>
                     <l>Which waſh fat <hi>Tybur,</hi> and Groues thickly growne,</l>
                     <l>Shall make his worth in <hi>Lyrick</hi> Verſe be ſhowne.</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Rome</hi> Queene of Cities, doth no whit diſdaine</l>
                     <l>Mee for the Muſes ſake to entertaine</l>
                     <l>Amongſt the Poets, loued Quires to ſit,</l>
                     <l>So that I now, am leſſe with Enuy bit.</l>
                     <l>(Oh thou <hi>Pierian)</hi> which with Harpe of gold,</l>
                     <l>Doſt in ſweet notes harmonious ayre vnfold;</l>
                     <l>(Oh thou) who if thou pleaſe, to Fiſhes mute,</l>
                     <l>The Swan's delicious Song canſt attribute:</l>
                     <l>It wholly is a gift deriu'd from thee,</l>
                     <l>That by each finger, which doth paſſe by me,</l>
                     <l>The <hi>Romane Lyrick</hi> Harper they deſigne.</l>
                     <l>That I doe breath, and pleaſe (if pleaſe) is thine.</l>
                  </lg>
               </div>
               <div n="5" type="ode">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Ode</hi> V. To AVGSTVS.</head>
                  <argument>
                     <p>
                        <hi>That now at length he would returne into the Citie.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </argument>
                  <lg>
                     <head>Diuis orte bonis.</head>
                     <l>
                        <hi>(CAeſar.)</hi> thou from the gods propitious ſprong,</l>
                     <l>Our beſt preſeruer, ſtay'ſt away too long.</l>
                     <l>Wee promiſe of thy quicke returne require,</l>
                     <l>Made to the ſacred Senate: Oh retire,</l>
                     <pb n="52" facs="tcp:4433:32"/>
                     <l>(Good <hi>Caeſar)</hi> on thy Countrey light reflect,</l>
                     <l>For where thy Spring-like face doth beames eiect,</l>
                     <l>More ioyfull to the people are the dayes,</l>
                     <l>And better doth the Sunne, transfuſe his rayes.</l>
                     <l>Like as a Mother (when the Southerne wind,</l>
                     <l>Her ſonne with enuious tempeſt hath confin'd,</l>
                     <l>Beyond the billowes of <hi>Carpathian</hi> Straights</l>
                     <l>More then a yeare:) His home-returne a waights</l>
                     <l>With vowes, and prayers; And the gods implores,</l>
                     <l>Her ey not ſtirring from the crooked ſhores.</l>
                     <l>So ſtrucken with their faithfull heart's deſire,</l>
                     <l>Thy Countrey <hi>(Caeſar)</hi> doth thy ſelfe require.</l>
                     <l>Behold the Oxe, ſafe, wandreth vp and downe;</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Ceres,</hi> and bright <hi>Felicitie</hi> doe crowne,</l>
                     <l>And feed the Land. The Seas are calmer fram'd</l>
                     <l>For <hi>Saylers</hi> vſe. Faith feareth to be blam'd.</l>
                     <l>No chaſt houſe, with Adulterie's defil'd;</l>
                     <l>Cuſtome, and Law, hath ſpotted ſinne exil'd.</l>
                     <l>For Sonnes like Syres, the Mothers we commend.</l>
                     <l>"Companion puniſhment doth vice attend.</l>
                     <l>Who feares the <hi>Parthian</hi> now, or <hi>Scythian</hi> bold;</l>
                     <l>Or Monſters, which rough <hi>Germany</hi> doth hold.</l>
                     <l>Or <hi>Caeſar</hi> being ſafe, who will regard,</l>
                     <l>That fierce <hi>Iberia</hi> ſtands for armes prepar'd?</l>
                     <l>Each man in his owne hilles, doth cloſe the day,</l>
                     <l>And Vines about the widow-Elme diſplay.</l>
                     <l>Then frolike to his banquet hee retires,</l>
                     <l>And thee a god, in ſecond Cups admires.</l>
                     <l>With many prayers, he doth his Vowes enflame,</l>
                     <l>And powres full goblets out vnto thy name;</l>
                     <pb n="53" facs="tcp:4433:32"/>
                     <l>Thy Godhead ſeeking with his <hi>Lars</hi> to pleaſe,</l>
                     <l>As <hi>Greece</hi> their <hi>Caeſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>r,</hi> and great <hi>Hercules.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>(Good <hi>Caeſar)</hi> render long repoſe we pray,</l>
                     <l>To glad <hi>Heſperia:</hi> This wee (ſober) ſay</l>
                     <l>When day firſt breaks: This moyſtned, when to reſt</l>
                     <l>The Sun inuites vs, wa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ing in the Weſt.</l>
                  </lg>
               </div>
               <div n="7" type="ode">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Ode</hi> VII. To LVCIVS MANLIVS TORQVATVS.</head>
                  <argument>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Since Time changeth all things, let vs liue merily.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </argument>
                  <lg>
                     <head>Diffugêre niues.</head>
                     <l>NOw ſnows are quite diſſolu'd, freſh graſſe we ſee</l>
                     <l>To fields return'd, and leaues to euery tree.</l>
                     <l>The earth with various change each ſeaſon rankes,</l>
                     <l>And falling Riuers glide within their bankes.</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Aglaia</hi> dareth (naked) on the ground,</l>
                     <l>With Nimphes, and her two ſiſters daunce a-round.</l>
                     <l>The yeare vs warnes immortall things to doubt,</l>
                     <l>And Hower, which circumvolues the day about.</l>
                     <l>Soft Weſterne winds, on Winter mildneſſe bring,</l>
                     <l>Soone wither'd Summer, weareth out the Spring,</l>
                     <l>Then mellow Autumne, powres his fruits amaine,</l>
                     <l>And inſtantly dull Winter turnes againe.</l>
                     <l>Yet ſpeedy Moones celeſtiall harmes reſtore</l>
                     <l>To after times: when wee are gone before,</l>
                     <pb n="54" facs="tcp:4433:33"/>
                     <l>Where <hi>Tullus,</hi> good <hi>Aeneas, Ancus</hi> trade,</l>
                     <l>Nought are wee elſe (alas) but duſt, and ſhade.</l>
                     <l>Who is it knowes, whether the heauenly powers,</l>
                     <l>Will adde to this dayes ſumme to morrow's howers.</l>
                     <l>Your greedy heire in nothing ſhall haue part,</l>
                     <l>Which you in life ſhall giue with bounteous heart.</l>
                     <l>But when you once are dead, and powers diuine,</l>
                     <l>To you, an equall ſentence ſhall aſſigne;</l>
                     <l>Then (oh <hi>Torquatus)</hi> blood, nor eloquence,</l>
                     <l>Nor pietie, can life againe diſpenſe:</l>
                     <l>For neither chaſt <hi>Hypolitus,</hi> was free</l>
                     <l>By <hi>Dian</hi> ſet, from Hells obſcuritie;</l>
                     <l>Nor were <hi>Laethean</hi> bands, by <hi>Theſeus</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Diſſolued, for his deare <hi>Pyritho<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>us.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </lg>
               </div>
               <div n="8" type="ode">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Ode</hi> VIII. To MARTIVS CENSORINVS.</head>
                  <argument>
                     <p>
                        <hi>There is nothing which can more immortalize men, then Poets Verſes.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </argument>
                  <lg>
                     <head>Donarem pateras.</head>
                     <l>TO friends I would giue freely <hi>(Cenſorine)</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Pieces of richeſt Plate, and Bowles for Wine,</l>
                     <l>Three-footed Tables, (valiant Greekes reward:)</l>
                     <l>Nor from my choyceſt gifts ſhould you be barr'd,</l>
                     <pb n="55" facs="tcp:4433:33"/>
                     <l>Were I with artfull figures richly ſped,</l>
                     <l>Which <hi>Parrhaſe</hi> drew, or <hi>Scopas</hi> pourtrayed.</l>
                     <l>In colours one, in ſtone the other bold,</l>
                     <l>A man ſometimes, ſometimes a God to mould.</l>
                     <l>But I haue not this power: Nor doe ſuppoſe,</l>
                     <l>Your wealth, or wiſh, wants ſuch delights, as thoſe.</l>
                     <l>You Verſes loue, for Verſe we make a ſhift,</l>
                     <l>And know what price to ſet on ſuch a guift;</l>
                     <l>Not Marbles with deepe Characters engrau'd,</l>
                     <l>By which to valiant Captaines life is ſau'd,</l>
                     <l>And ſpirit after death: Not ſpeedy flight,</l>
                     <l>Nor threats of <hi>Hanniball,</hi> reiected quite:</l>
                     <l>Not flames of <hi>Carthage</hi> better ſound his praiſe,</l>
                     <l>Who did his name from conquer'd <hi>Affrick</hi> raiſe,</l>
                     <l>Then <hi>Ennius</hi> Muſe: Nor can reward bee wonne,</l>
                     <l>If paper tell not, what was brauely done.</l>
                     <l>What would become of <hi>Mars,</hi> and <hi>Illia's</hi> brood,</l>
                     <l>If ſpitefull ſilence, <hi>Romulus</hi> withſtood?</l>
                     <l>The ſtrength, and grace of Poets powerfull wit,</l>
                     <l>Makes <hi>Aeacus</hi> in fields <hi>Elizian</hi> ſir,</l>
                     <l>Snatched from <hi>Stygian</hi> floods. "Muſes denie,</l>
                     <l>A man deſeruing praiſe ſhould euer die.</l>
                     <l>"Muſes giue heau'n: So dauntleſſe <hi>Hercules,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>In <hi>loues</hi> wiſh'd Banquets doth his palate pleaſe:</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Caſtor</hi> and <hi>Pollux</hi> bright Starre doth redeeme,</l>
                     <l>Storme-beaten Veſſels, which do ſhipwrack'd ſeeme.</l>
                     <l>God <hi>Bacchus</hi> brow, adorn'd with verdant Vine,</l>
                     <l>Doth happy end, vnto our vowes aſſigne.</l>
                  </lg>
               </div>
               <div n="13" type="ode">
                  <pb n="56" facs="tcp:4433:34"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>Ode</hi> XIII. To VIRGILL.</head>
                  <argument>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Hee deſcribeth the approach of the Spring, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiteth</hi> Virgil <hi>vnder condition to a Banquet.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </argument>
                  <lg>
                     <head>Iam veris comites.</head>
                     <l>SOuth winds, the Spring attending ſtill,</l>
                     <l>Now Seas doe calme, and Sayles doe fill:</l>
                     <l>Now Froſtes doe not make Meadowes hore,</l>
                     <l>Nor Winter-Snow, ſwolne Riuers rore.</l>
                     <l>The luckleſſe Bird, her neſt doth frame,</l>
                     <l>Bewayling <hi>Itis,</hi> and the ſhame,</l>
                     <l>Of <hi>Cecrops</hi> houſe; and that ſo ill,</l>
                     <l>On Kings rude luſt, ſhee wrought her will.</l>
                     <l>The Shepheards of rich Flocks rehearſe,</l>
                     <l>And to their Pipes chaunt rurall Verſe:</l>
                     <l>And ſeeke his God-head to appeaſe,</l>
                     <l>Whom flockes, and hills <hi>Arcadian</hi> pleaſe.</l>
                     <l>Theſe times doe thirſtie Seaſons ſend:</l>
                     <l>But if (thou <hi>Virgill) Caeſar's</hi> friend,</l>
                     <l>With preſs'd <hi>Calenian</hi> Liquor hie,</l>
                     <l>For Wine, thou ſhalt ſweet vnguents buy,</l>
                     <l>And purchaſe with a little Box,</l>
                     <l>Wine, which <hi>Sulpitius</hi> ſafely locks.</l>
                     <pb n="57" facs="tcp:4433:34"/>
                     <l>New hopes moſt powerfull to create,</l>
                     <l>And bitter ca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>es to diſſipate.</l>
                     <l>Vnto which comfort, if thou haſt,</l>
                     <l>Come hither with thy Vnguents faſt.</l>
                     <l>I'le not (free cost) my cupps carrotiſe,</l>
                     <l>As rich men in a plenteous houſe.</l>
                     <l>Then leaue delayes, and Gaine's deſire,</l>
                     <l>And mindfull of blacke Funerall fire,</l>
                     <l>"Short folly mixe with Councells beſt.</l>
                     <l>"Tis ſweet, ſometime to bee in ieſt.</l>
                  </lg>
               </div>
               <div n="13" type="ode">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Ode</hi> XIII. Againſt LYCE.</head>
                  <argument>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Who being olde, it become a ſcorne to young men.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </argument>
                  <lg>
                     <head>Audiuere Lyce.</head>
                     <l>THe gods haue <hi>(Lyce)</hi> heard my vow,</l>
                     <l>My vow is heard. Th'art old, yet thou,</l>
                     <l>Vaine would'ſt (forſooth) bee counted faire,</l>
                     <l>And quaffe, and wanton with the ayre:</l>
                     <l>And (dru<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="3 letters">
                           <desc>•••</desc>
                        </gap>e) with trembling voyee invite</l>
                     <l>Slow <hi>Cupid;</hi> who <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> more delight,</l>
                     <pb n="58" facs="tcp:4433:35"/>
                     <l>On <hi>Chia's</hi> roſie cheekes to ſtay,</l>
                     <l>Both young, and skill'd in Muſick's lay.</l>
                     <l>For hee, delay not booking, flies</l>
                     <l>From wither'd Okes; and from thee hies,</l>
                     <l>Whom rotten teeth, and wrinckled face,</l>
                     <l>And head of ſnowy hayre, diſgrace.</l>
                     <l>Now cannot <hi>Coa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>n</hi> Purple's vſe,</l>
                     <l>Nor brighteſt gemms, the <hi>Time</hi> reduce,</l>
                     <l>Which once ſwift-winged <hi>Age</hi> hath cloſ'd</l>
                     <l>In publique Calenders diſpoſ'd.</l>
                     <l>Where is thy beautie fled? (Ay mee)</l>
                     <l>Thy colour freſh, and motion free?</l>
                     <l>What haſt thou of that, that entire,</l>
                     <l>Which earſt inſpired amorous fire?</l>
                     <l>And did mee from my ſelfe diuert;</l>
                     <l>Next <hi>Cynaras,</hi> thou happy wert,</l>
                     <l>For pleaſing beautie, and ſweet grace,</l>
                     <l>Diſcou'red in a louely face.</l>
                     <l>But Fates to <hi>Cynaras</hi> did owe,</l>
                     <l>Short life, and <hi>Lyce</hi> like the Crowe;</l>
                     <l>They heere ſuruiuing longer hold,</l>
                     <l>That ſeruent young men may behold.</l>
                     <l>Not without laughter, and much ſcorne,</l>
                     <l>A flaming torch to aſhes worne.</l>
                  </lg>
               </div>
               <div n="15" type="ode">
                  <pb n="59" facs="tcp:4433:35"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>Ode</hi> XV.</head>
                  <argument>
                     <p>
                        <hi>The prayſes of</hi> Auguſtus.</p>
                  </argument>
                  <lg>
                     <head>Phaebus volentem.</head>
                     <l>MY Muſe by <hi>Phebus</hi> was rebuk'd of late,</l>
                     <l>For ſinging warres, and vanquiſh'd cities fate:</l>
                     <l>Like thoſe, who in the <hi>Tyrren</hi> Ocean's rage,</l>
                     <l>Doe little Sayles aduance. <hi>(Caeſar)</hi> thy age,</l>
                     <l>Affoordeth plenteous fruits, vnto the fields,</l>
                     <l>And to <hi>Ioues</hi> Capitoll our Enſignes yeelds,</l>
                     <l>From <hi>Parthian</hi> Pillars ſnatch'd, and after iarres</l>
                     <l>Hath cloſed <hi>Ianus</hi> Temple free from warres.</l>
                     <l>Confuſion hath with Order rectifi'd,</l>
                     <l>And wandring Libertie in fetters ty'd.</l>
                     <l>Hath antique arts recall'd: By which tis knowne</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Heſperia's</hi> ſtrength and <hi>Latine</hi> name hath growne.</l>
                     <l>Imperiall pompe hath ſpred, and glory wonne,</l>
                     <l>Stretcht from the riſing, to the ſetting Sunne.</l>
                     <l>While <hi>Caeſar</hi> is our Guardian, ciuill warre,</l>
                     <l>Nor violence, our peacefull reſt, ſhall marre.</l>
                     <l>Not anger, which ſwords ſharpeneth, and confounds</l>
                     <l>Cities, vnhappy made with mutuall wounds.</l>
                     <l>Not they for thirſt, that drinke in <hi>Iſter</hi> deepe,</l>
                     <l>Shall once refuſe, the <hi>Iulian</hi> Lawes to keepe.</l>
                     <pb n="60" facs="tcp:4433:36"/>
                     <l>Not <hi>Seres,</hi> faithleſſe <hi>Perſians,</hi> nor the <hi>Getes,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Nor thoſe, which neere to <hi>Tanais</hi> haue their ſeats.</l>
                     <l>And wee on holy Eeues, and holy Dayes,</l>
                     <l>Amongſt free Cupps, to merry <hi>Bacchus</hi> prayſe:</l>
                     <l>With wife, and children, ſtanding in our ſight.</l>
                     <l>(Firſt Gods inuoking with religious Rite)</l>
                     <l>Will gladly (as our grandſires did) rehearſe,</l>
                     <l>(And tuning <hi>Lydian</hi> Pipe to various Verſe,)</l>
                     <l>Heroique Captaines, <hi>Troy, Anobiſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>gone,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>And braue <hi>Aeneas, Cytherea's</hi> ſonne.</l>
                  </lg>
               </div>
            </div>
            <trailer>The end of the fourth Booke.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="epodes">
            <pb n="61" facs="tcp:4433:36"/>
            <head>CERTAINE EPODS OF <hi>HORACE</hi>
            </head>
            <div n="1" type="epode">
               <head>
                  <hi>Epod</hi> I. To MAECEMAS.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>Horace <hi>will wa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="3 letters">
                           <desc>•••</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </hi> M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ccn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>, <hi>going to the</hi> Actiack <hi>war<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="3 letters">
                           <desc>•••</desc>
                        </gap> againſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </hi> Anthony.</p>
               </argument>
               <lg>
                  <head>I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> lib<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>nis.</head>
                  <l>IN low built <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>arkes, thou wilt not faile,</l>
                  <l>'Mongſt loftie tow<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ing Ships to ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>yle;</l>
                  <l>And doſt <hi>(Macenas)</hi> much e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>cline,</l>
                  <l>To make great <hi>Caeſar's</hi> p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rill thi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>.</l>
                  <l>What ſhall wee doe? Whoſe life is bleſt,</l>
                  <l>If thou ſurniue: If not, diſtreſt.</l>
                  <l>Shall wee (commanded) idle bee:</l>
                  <l>Repoſe is toyle, if not with thee.</l>
                  <pb n="62" facs="tcp:4433:37"/>
                  <l>Or ſhall wee vndergoe theſe paynes,</l>
                  <l>With minds which no ſoft eaſe reſtraines?</l>
                  <l>Wee will? And through the <hi>Alpes</hi> aſcent,</l>
                  <l>And <hi>Caucaſus,</hi> where none frequent:</l>
                  <l>Yea to the vtmoſt Weſterne parts,</l>
                  <l>Will follow thee, with conſtant hearts.</l>
                  <l>You'le aske; How can thy labour pleaſe,</l>
                  <l>Vntrayn'd in armes, and weake with eaſe?</l>
                  <l>"In company, Feares little ſeeme,</l>
                  <l>Which men in abſence, great eſteeme.</l>
                  <l>As Bird, her plumeleſſe young ones, left,</l>
                  <l>More feares to find by Serpents reſt;</l>
                  <l>Not that ſhee can with preſence, bring</l>
                  <l>Force able to reſiſt the ſting.</l>
                  <l>This warrfare will I vndertake,</l>
                  <l>Or any other, for thy ſake.</l>
                  <l>Not that my many Ploughes are found,</l>
                  <l>With Oxen more, to till the ground.</l>
                  <l>Or Beaſts to <hi>Lucan</hi> Meads are ſent,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Calabrian</hi> feruors to preuent.</l>
                  <l>Nor <hi>Tuſculum,</hi> my Village cleare,</l>
                  <l>May to <hi>Circaean</hi> walls, come neare.</l>
                  <l>Thy fauour mee enough hath ſtoar'd,</l>
                  <l>Which I, as <hi>Chremes</hi> will not <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>oard</l>
                  <l>Within the earth, nor euer ſhall</l>
                  <l>Spend like a waſtfull prodigall.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="epode">
               <pb n="63" facs="tcp:4433:37"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>Epod</hi> II.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>
                     <hi>The praiſe of the Countrey life.</hi>
                  </p>
               </argument>
               <lg>
                  <head>Beatus ille qui procul negotijs.</head>
                  <l>HEe happy is, who farre from buſie toyle,</l>
                  <l>(As elder ages) tills the ſoyle</l>
                  <l>With his owne Cattle, which his father left,</l>
                  <l>From thralling intereſt bereft.</l>
                  <l>Hee is n<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ot moou'd, when warlike Drumms doe beat,</l>
                  <l>Nor feares the angry Ocean's threat.</l>
                  <l>Hee Pleas, and Suits abhorres, and doth refuſe,</l>
                  <l>The grace of mightie men to vſe.</l>
                  <l>But either doth to talleſt Poplars twine,</l>
                  <l>The tender off-ſprings of the Vine.</l>
                  <l>And cutting branches off, which vſeleſſe were,</l>
                  <l>Graft thoſe, which better fruit may beare.</l>
                  <l>Or, vieweth in ſome winding valley's maze,</l>
                  <l>His wand'ring Heards of Cattle, graze.</l>
                  <l>Or, doth preſs'd honey in pure veſſells keepe,</l>
                  <l>Or, ſheare his wooll o're-burdned ſheepe.</l>
                  <l>But when with mellow fruit ripe <hi>Autumne</hi> crown'd,</l>
                  <l>His head vpreareth from the ground.</l>
                  <l>How he to taſt the grafted Peare delights,</l>
                  <l>And grape, that with the Purple fights.</l>
                  <l>Which to <hi>Priapus,</hi> as a gift redounds,</l>
                  <l>Or, old <hi>Siluanus,</hi> God of Bounds.</l>
                  <pb n="64" facs="tcp:4433:38"/>
                  <l>Now vnder aged Oke, hee howers doth paſſe,</l>
                  <l>And now repoſeth on the graſſe.</l>
                  <l>While gentle Riuers from high bankes doe glide,</l>
                  <l>And Birds their warbling notes diuide:</l>
                  <l>Small ſtreames, on purling pibbles murmure keepe,</l>
                  <l>To ſummon ſoft, and eaſie ſleepe.</l>
                  <l>But when lowd <hi>loue,</hi> rough Winter ſends below,</l>
                  <l>In ſtormy ſhowres, and chilling ſnow.</l>
                  <l>Then hee the hardy Bore, from place to place,</l>
                  <l>With Fleet-Hounds, into Toyles doth chace:</l>
                  <l>Or elſe, the fearefull Hare, and fortaine Crane</l>
                  <l>With pleaſing ſpoyle, in grinns are ta'ne.</l>
                  <l>Ah! who in thought, 'mongſt ſuch delights retaines</l>
                  <l>Leaſt ſenſe, of loue's diſturbing paines?</l>
                  <l>But if (in part) a modeſt wife direct</l>
                  <l>The houſe, and children deare affect.</l>
                  <l>As <hi>Sabine</hi> earſt, or ſwift <hi>Apuli<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>'s</hi> dame,</l>
                  <l>Parched with tawney <hi>Phebus</hi> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>la<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>e,</l>
                  <l>With old dry w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>od, a bleſs'd fire make to burne,</l>
                  <l>'Gainſt weary husband's wiſh'd returne:</l>
                  <l>And folding glad ſome ſtocks in wouen grates,</l>
                  <l>Dryes vp their dugges, which milke dil<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>es;</l>
                  <l>And broaching new wines kept in veſſells faire,</l>
                  <l>An (vnbought) Supper doth prepare.</l>
                  <l>The <hi>L<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>trine Oyſter</hi> (ſure) not <hi>G<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>head</hi> bright,</l>
                  <l>Nor <hi>Turbot,</hi> ye<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ldeth more delight;</l>
                  <l>If Winter ſuch, when Eaſterne tempeſts rore,</l>
                  <l>Doe driue vpon our <hi>Terrhene</hi> ſhore.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Ionick Partriges,</hi> not <hi>Affrick Quaile,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Vpon my palate more preuaile,</l>
                  <pb n="65" facs="tcp:4433:38"/>
                  <l>Then doth the vnctuous Oliue choycely cull'd,</l>
                  <l>From fertile Branches newly pull'd:</l>
                  <l>Or Sorrell that in Meadowes doth abound,</l>
                  <l>And Mellowes, bodies making ſound.</l>
                  <l>Or Lambe, on <hi>Terminus</hi> his Feaſt th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>t dies,</l>
                  <l>Or Kidd redeem'd, from Wolfe's ſurpriſe.</l>
                  <l>Amongſt theſe dainties, what content it yeelds,</l>
                  <l>To ſee the fed-ſtocks leaue the fields.</l>
                  <l>To ſee the weary O<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e with neck worne ba<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e,</l>
                  <l>Dregging the turned plough and ſhare:</l>
                  <l>And Hinds (the plenteous houſhold ſwarme)</l>
                  <l>'Bout ſhining <hi>L<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>rs</hi> to ſit, and warme.</l>
                  <l>This ſayd, rich <hi>Al<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>hins</hi> that money lends,</l>
                  <l>To lead a Countrey life intends;</l>
                  <l>And in the <hi>Ides</hi> his De<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap> call'd in amaine,</l>
                  <l>But in the <hi>Calends</hi> lent againe.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="epode">
               <head>
                  <hi>Epod</hi> VII. To the people of ROME.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>
                     <hi>An Exetration of the ci<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ill warre, raiſed, on the one ſide by</hi> B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </hi> Caſſius; <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> the other, by</hi> O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctauian, M. Anthony, <hi>and</hi> Lepidu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>the Roman Conſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>lls.</hi>
                  </p>
               </argument>
               <lg>
                  <head>Quo, quo ſceleſti.</head>
                  <l>AH Tr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ytors, whither haſt you? To what end,</l>
                  <l>Do your right ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds, to ſhethed ſwords deſcend?</l>
                  <pb n="66" facs="tcp:4433:39"/>
                  <l>Is there ſo little yet, of <hi>Latine</hi> blood,</l>
                  <l>Powr'd on the Champaine fields, or Ocean flood?</l>
                  <l>Not that the <hi>Roman</hi> ſhould with flames abate,</l>
                  <l>The Towers of <hi>Carthage,</hi> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="4 letters">
                        <desc>••••</desc>
                     </gap>ous of our ſtate:</l>
                  <l>Or <hi>Britton</hi> ſhould (vnconquered to this day)</l>
                  <l>Bee taught, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> chaln<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ead the Pacred way.</l>
                  <l>But that (which now <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>lie Pa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>hian would de<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>nd)</l>
                  <l>This Citie ſhould bee <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> by ciuill hand.</l>
                  <l>'Mongſt Wol<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>s, and Lyons neuer was this vſe,</l>
                  <l>But beaſts, whom nature diffrent doth produce.</l>
                  <l>Doth Fury blind? Or greater power command?</l>
                  <l>Or ſinne's offence? Oh let me vnderſtand?</l>
                  <l>They ſilent are: Th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </l>
                  <l>And feares their horror-ſtrucken minds inuade.</l>
                  <l>'Tis ſo: Sowre <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ates doe <hi>Rome</hi> with fury ſtaine,</l>
                  <l>And tyrannous offence of brother flame.</l>
                  <l>Which on enſuing ages layd the guilt,</l>
                  <l>When <hi>Remus</hi> harmleſſe blood on earth was ſpilt.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div n="13" type="epode">
               <head>
                  <hi>Epod.</hi> XIII.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>To his merry fri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ds, that they ſhould paſſe the W<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>er <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </p>
               </argument>
               <lg>
                  <head>H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>rida tempeſtas.</head>
                  <l>ROugh tempeſts haue the brow of heauen bent,</l>
                  <l>And ſhowres, and ſnowe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>, cauſe thi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="4 letters">
                        <desc>••••</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="5 letters">
                        <desc>•••••</desc>
                     </gap>e's deſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ent.</l>
                  <pb n="67" facs="tcp:4433:39"/>
                  <l>Now <hi>Thracian</hi> Northwinds, Sea, and woods affray.</l>
                  <l>Friends, let vs take occaſion, from the day;</l>
                  <l>While ſtrength is freſh, and vs it well becomes,</l>
                  <l>Let Age be lightned, which the brow benummes.</l>
                  <l>Boy, ſee you broach thoſe elder wines were preſs'd,</l>
                  <l>When <hi>Torquate</hi> firſt, the Conſull's place poſſeſs'd.</l>
                  <l>Speake not of other things. God will perchance,</l>
                  <l>Theſe to their ſeat, with happy change aduance.</l>
                  <l>Vnguents of <hi>Perſian</hi> Odours, now delight;</l>
                  <l>Cares driuing with <hi>Cylenian</hi> Harpe to flight;</l>
                  <l>As noble <hi>Chiron</hi> to <hi>Achilles</hi> ſang.</l>
                  <l>Vnvanquiſh'd Mortall, that from <hi>Thetis</hi> ſprang,</l>
                  <l>Thee <hi>Troy</hi> expects; which <hi>Simois</hi> rowling Tyde,</l>
                  <l>And ſmall <hi>Scamander's</hi> colder ſtreames diuide,</l>
                  <l>Whence to returne, ſo Fates thy threed vndoe,</l>
                  <l>Thou canſt not back with thy blew Mother goe.</l>
                  <l>All Sorrow there, with wine, and Song depreſſe,</l>
                  <l>(Sweet comforts, of deformed heauineſſe.)</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <trailer>The end of the Epods.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
